<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Vibecoding on Vijay Kodam</title>
    <link>https://vijay.eu/tags/vibecoding/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Vibecoding on Vijay Kodam</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 16:29:33 +0300</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://vijay.eu/tags/vibecoding/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Built an app using Lovable, vibecoding startup</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/ai-lab/lovable-app/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 16:29:33 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/ai-lab/lovable-app/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Built a game using &lt;a href=&#34;https://lovable.dev/&#34;&gt;Lovable&lt;/a&gt;, a vibe-coding AI platform, this weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovable organized AI Showdown during the weekend where users can build projects and compete using code-generating AI Models from OpenAI, Anthropic and Google.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of my project, I have created a simple word ladder game, where the player can only change only single letter in each rung to add a valid English word. The game is to change the existing word one letter at a time into the target word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/lovable.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;snowdrop&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the first time I am using Lovable and I am surprised by the maturity of the product. It is very intuitive to use and it creates complete working app in the first prompt itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent 2 hours creating this game, mainly to improve the word list, figure out to build huge amount of valid 3, 4 and 5 letter words, test the functionality, change the UI, check for security issues, change the UX etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anton Osika and team has built an amazing product. Also happy that it is from the Nordics :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feel free to try the game and give me your feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Game URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://word-ladder.lovable.app/&#34;&gt;https://word-ladder.lovable.app/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are new to my posts, I regularly post about AWS, EKS, Kubernetes and Cloud computing related topics. Do follow me in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vijaykodam/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; and visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.to/vijaykodam&#34;&gt;my dev.to posts&lt;/a&gt;. You can find all my previous blog posts in &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/posts&#34;&gt;my blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
