<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Vijay Kodam</title>
    <link>https://vijay.eu/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Vijay Kodam</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 10 Jan 2026 10:00:00 +0300</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://vijay.eu/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Cricket Bowling</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/projects/cricket-bowling/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Jan 2026 10:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/projects/cricket-bowling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;cricket-bowling-container&#34;&gt;
    &lt;header class=&#34;cricket-header&#34;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&#34;brand&#34;&gt;
            &lt;div class=&#34;brand__title&#34;&gt;Cricket Bowling&lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&#34;brand__subtitle&#34;&gt;Grip, bowl, and hit the wickets! Hand tracking in your browser.&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;

        &lt;div class=&#34;status&#34; aria-live=&#34;polite&#34;&gt;
            &lt;span class=&#34;badge badge--phase&#34; id=&#34;statusPhase&#34;&gt;Ready&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&#34;badge&#34; id=&#34;statusSpeed&#34;&gt;Speed: --&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&#34;badge&#34; id=&#34;statusBallType&#34;&gt;--&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&#34;badge badge--score&#34; id=&#34;statusScore&#34;&gt;Wickets: 0/0&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&#34;badge badge--muted&#34; id=&#34;statusFps&#34;&gt;FPS: --&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/header&gt;

    &lt;main class=&#34;cricket-layout&#34;&gt;
        &lt;section class=&#34;panel&#34;&gt;
            &lt;div class=&#34;panel__header&#34;&gt;
                &lt;h2 class=&#34;panel__title&#34;&gt;Camera&lt;/h2&gt;
                &lt;div class=&#34;panel__actions&#34;&gt;
                    &lt;button class=&#34;btn btn--primary&#34; id=&#34;btnWebcam&#34; type=&#34;button&#34;&gt;Enable webcam&lt;/button&gt;
                    &lt;button class=&#34;btn&#34; id=&#34;btnOverlay&#34; type=&#34;button&#34; aria-pressed=&#34;true&#34;&gt;Overlay: On&lt;/button&gt;
                &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;

            &lt;div class=&#34;media&#34;&gt;
                &lt;div class=&#34;media__stack&#34;&gt;
                    &lt;video id=&#34;webcam&#34; playsinline autoplay muted&gt;&lt;/video&gt;
                    &lt;canvas id=&#34;overlay2d&#34; class=&#34;overlay2d&#34; aria-hidden=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/canvas&gt;
                &lt;/div&gt;

                &lt;div class=&#34;hint&#34; id=&#34;gameHint&#34;&gt;
                    &lt;strong&gt;How to play:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
                    1. Close your fist to grip the ball&lt;br&gt;
                    2. Make a bowling motion (arm forward/down)&lt;br&gt;
                    3. Open your hand to release&lt;br&gt;
                    4. Try to hit the wickets!
                &lt;/div&gt;

                &lt;div class=&#34;result-display hidden&#34; id=&#34;resultDisplay&#34;&gt;
                    &lt;div class=&#34;result-icon&#34; id=&#34;resultIcon&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
                    &lt;div class=&#34;result-text&#34; id=&#34;resultText&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
                    &lt;div class=&#34;result-details&#34; id=&#34;resultDetails&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
                    &lt;div class=&#34;result-hint&#34;&gt;Close fist to bowl again&lt;/div&gt;
                &lt;/div&gt;

                &lt;div class=&#34;error hidden&#34; id=&#34;cameraError&#34; role=&#34;alert&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;

            &lt;div class=&#34;game-stats&#34;&gt;
                &lt;div class=&#34;stat-row&#34;&gt;
                    &lt;span class=&#34;stat-label&#34;&gt;Fast balls:&lt;/span&gt;
                    &lt;span class=&#34;stat-value&#34; id=&#34;statFast&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;/div&gt;
                &lt;div class=&#34;stat-row&#34;&gt;
                    &lt;span class=&#34;stat-label&#34;&gt;Spin balls:&lt;/span&gt;
                    &lt;span class=&#34;stat-value&#34; id=&#34;statSpin&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/section&gt;

        &lt;section class=&#34;panel&#34;&gt;
            &lt;div class=&#34;panel__header&#34;&gt;
                &lt;h2 class=&#34;panel__title&#34;&gt;3D Scene&lt;/h2&gt;
                &lt;div class=&#34;panel__actions&#34;&gt;
                    &lt;button class=&#34;btn&#34; id=&#34;btnReset&#34; type=&#34;button&#34;&gt;Reset Game&lt;/button&gt;
                &lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;

            &lt;div class=&#34;scene&#34;&gt;
                &lt;canvas id=&#34;threeCanvas&#34;&gt;&lt;/canvas&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;

            &lt;footer class=&#34;cricket-footer&#34;&gt;
                &lt;span class=&#34;muted&#34;&gt;Tip: Good lighting helps hand tracking. Works best on Chrome/Safari.&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;/footer&gt;
        &lt;/section&gt;
    &lt;/main&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2025 Year in Review</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/2025-year-in-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 19:16:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/2025-year-in-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/snowdrop.png&#34; alt=&#34;snowdrop&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Youtube video &lt;iframe 
  src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/HQK5P_Mbp1g?si=LA5Z9swDLv6T7NgP&#34; 
  width=&#34;560&#34; 
  height=&#34;315&#34; 
  title=&#34;Embedded Content&#34; 
  frameborder=&#34;0&#34; 
  allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&#34; 
  referrerpolicy=&#34;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&#34;
  allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you had told me at the start of the year that I would speak at major Amazon Web Services (AWS) and Microsoft conferences in Europe, I would have called it unlikely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2025 has been an amazing year for me. Not only I got the chance to speak at AWS Summit and Microsoft AgentCon and other conferences, I also got certified, completed GenAI courses, built MCP servers and AI agents and much more. I have spent countless hours after work this year to achieve those things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few highlights for me in 2025:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Became AWS Community Builder for the first time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Passed AWS Certified AI Practitioner from Amazon Web Services (AWS)!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Created my own Kubernetes Read Only MCP server&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Created my own AI Agent for Autonomous Troubleshooting K8s operations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delivered presentations at AWS Summit Zurich, Microsoft’s AgentCon and AWS Nordics Community Day!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Won two GenAI hackathons at AWS Summit Stockholm and another at AWS event in Helsinki!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learnt a lot in hashtag#GenAI including “Building Agentic AI Applications with a Problem-First Approach”, “AI evals” and Google’s GenAI and AI Agent courses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Built multiple AI projects. “LLM pricing” project is the latest one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trained a neural network for my Le Robot SO-101 arm.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All throughout the year along my journey, many people helped me, inspired me and guided me. Thanks to all of you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are new to my posts, I regularly post about AWS, EKS, Kubernetes and Cloud computing related topics. Do follow me in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vijaykodam/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; and visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.to/vijaykodam&#34;&gt;my dev.to posts&lt;/a&gt;. You can find all my previous blog posts in &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/posts&#34;&gt;my blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>LLM Pricing Comparison</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/projects/llm-pricing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/projects/llm-pricing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Compare API pricing for text tokens across major Large Language Model providers. All prices are per 1 million tokens in USD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click on any column header to sort the table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;llm-pricing-container&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div id=&#34;llm-pricing-loading&#34;&gt;Loading pricing data...&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;div id=&#34;llm-pricing-error&#34; style=&#34;display: none;&#34;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Failed to load pricing data. Please try again later.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;table id=&#34;llm-pricing-table&#34; style=&#34;display: none;&#34;&gt;
        &lt;thead&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;th data-sort=&#34;provider&#34; class=&#34;sortable&#34;&gt;Provider&lt;/th&gt;
                &lt;th data-sort=&#34;model&#34; class=&#34;sortable&#34;&gt;Model&lt;/th&gt;
                &lt;th data-sort=&#34;input&#34; class=&#34;sortable&#34;&gt;Input / MTok&lt;/th&gt;
                &lt;th data-sort=&#34;cache_input&#34; class=&#34;sortable&#34;&gt;Cache Input / MTok&lt;/th&gt;
                &lt;th data-sort=&#34;output&#34; class=&#34;sortable&#34;&gt;Output / MTok&lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;/thead&gt;
        &lt;tbody id=&#34;llm-pricing-tbody&#34;&gt;
        &lt;/tbody&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;

    &lt;div id=&#34;llm-pricing-metadata&#34;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;llm-pricing-last-checked&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;llm-pricing-last-updated&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;div id=&#34;llm-pricing-sources&#34;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sources:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://platform.openai.com/docs/pricing#text-tokens&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;OpenAI API Pricing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.anthropic.com/en/docs/about-claude/models&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Anthropic Claude Pricing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ai.google.dev/gemini-api/docs/pricing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Google Gemini API Pricing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Amazon EKS Capabilities</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/eks-capabilities/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 20:39:13 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/eks-capabilities/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://dev-to-uploads.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/articles/a6l05jg2q2jt9i3tg15s.png&#34; alt=&#34;EKS Capabilities&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A quick summary typed by my own thumbs and infographic generated by Nano Banana Pro :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, AWS offloaded EKS node management and scaling by introducing EKS Auto Mode. Customers did not have to deal with scaling nodes, upgrading nodes etc. This gave the customers more time to deploy and manage their applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, EKS has decided to offload managing your ArgoCD, ACK and kro. EKS would manage them for you by running them separately. There are pros and cons for this feature. Pro being there is now one less thing to manage. Since ArgoCD, ACK and kro are not running in your EKS worker nodes, you don&amp;rsquo;t pay for them. AWS takes care of running them, scaling, upgrading them and making sure they are running fine. Con is that EKS charges it as part of EKS Capabilities pricing. Not all features might be supported. Customization is not possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So you need to decide whether this extra cost is worth it or not. It depends on the expertise of the team, how many clusters they are managing and how many applications each ArgoCD is managing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the pricing, number of ArgoCD applications dictates how costly it is going to be, rest all other features and capabilities are relatively cheaper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My dear friend Jatin Mehrotra wrote an &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.to/aws-builders/i-created-s3-buckets-using-argocd-ack-with-eks-capabilities-no-controllers-installed-cm0&#34;&gt;excellent blog&lt;/a&gt; about EKS capabilities and also found a bug.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Image generated using Nano Banana Pro.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are new to my posts, I regularly post about AWS, EKS, Kubernetes and Cloud computing related topics. Do follow me in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vijaykodam/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; and visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.to/vijaykodam&#34;&gt;my dev.to posts&lt;/a&gt;. You can find all my previous blog posts in &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/posts&#34;&gt;my blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Honest Take on Kiro, AI IDE from AWS</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/my-honest-take-on-kiro/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:24:38 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/my-honest-take-on-kiro/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/kiro-screenshot.png&#34; alt=&#34;kiro&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amazon Web Services (AWS) released Kiro, an agentic AI IDE yesterday. Built an app with it today. Here is my honest take of this new AI IDE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is my first experience trying Kiro and spent around 8 hours building a TODO app with Google OAuth2 authentication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-kiro&#34;&gt;What is Kiro?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AWS released an AI powered agentic IDE powered by Claude 4.0 Sonnet. Cursor and Windsurf are it&amp;rsquo;s competetors in this area. This area has been very hot with startups cloning VS Code and building AI code editors and several of them are worth couple of billion US dollars. You can learn more about Kiro at &lt;a href=&#34;https://kiro.dev/&#34;&gt;https://kiro.dev/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;vibe-code--spec-code&#34;&gt;Vibe Code &amp;amp; Spec Code&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kiro supports vibe-coding as well as spec-based coding. I felt that this is a good way to teach industry best practices for a non-software engineer on how to build a software project from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/spec-code.png&#34; alt=&#34;spec&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From your single line wish in natural language, it creates a big set of requirements, Design Document and properly structured Tasks list which includes not only functional tasks but also non-functional and security related tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once it is ready, you could review them, edit them and then run tasks one-by-one sequentially.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;important-features&#34;&gt;Important Features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two more concepts/features introduced by Kiro other than spec-driven development:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Agent Hooks and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Agent Steering.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/hooks.png&#34; alt=&#34;hooks&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;agent-hooks&#34;&gt;Agent Hooks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These hooks get called when an event occurs. Currently Agent hooks supports triggering based on file operations like create, save and delete. You then mention what the Agent should do when it is triggered in natural language. No scripting, no coding, just plain English.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a very short time, I found Agent hooks to be extremely useful.  I created an agent hook to add files to git and then git commit my changes after every task is successfully completed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is my Agent hook for git commit on file save:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/git-hook.png&#34; alt=&#34;githooks&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Icing on the cake was that the Agent hook actually read all my code changes, summarized and added a single line commit comment which mentions what changes were done. The power of LLMs is on display in this usecase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;agent-steering&#34;&gt;Agent Steering&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you click the created steering docs, Agent steering creates three docs: product, structure and tech stack. They contain all the info related to your project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the steering doc for project for my app:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/steering.png&#34; alt=&#34;steering&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could add your coding best practices, tech stack wish list, other conditions here, which will dictate how the code is generated by LLMs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-todo-app&#34;&gt;My TODO app&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I created a TODO app with Google sign-in as authentication method, without any AWS tech involved. Kiro is advertised as an independent AI IDE so I wanted to test that aspect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find the screenshots of the app in the images below.
&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/todoapp1.png&#34; alt=&#34;todoapp1&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/todoapp2.png&#34; alt=&#34;todoapp2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got a working app with working Google authentication. Tested it with my Gmail credentials and it was working flawlessly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;improvements&#34;&gt;Improvements?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Considering Kiro is released yesterday, I believe my impressions mentioned below might be resolved sooner or later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, here I go&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;model-choice&#34;&gt;Model Choice&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently Kiro is limited to only Claude 4.0 Sonnet and Claude 3.7 Sonnet. Honestly these two are the industry best for coding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there might be usecases where fast responses are preferred over best responses. In those case, I wish Nova models from AWS are available as a choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;slowness&#34;&gt;Slowness&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Few times faced slowness, although it is expected as there will be lot of people trying out Kiro along with Claude 4.0 Sonnet.
Claude 3.7 Sonnet felt bit more faster compared to 4.0 but considering the amount of people trying it out and being Kiro in preview phase, I can totally understand this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;agent-hooks-1&#34;&gt;Agent Hooks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I might have caught a bug in Agent Hooks implementation or I might be wrong. Anyway, let me spell it out. Feel free to correct me if I understood it wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While trying out Agent hooks, I have configured an Agent hook to be triggered whenever a file is saved. This worked fine if I run one task at a time. Whenever a file save was done, Agent hook was added to the task queue and waited until the tasks before it are done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After running one task at a time, I thought I will click &amp;ldquo;Start Task&amp;rdquo; on all the tasks so that all tasks will be executed sequentially. Here, when the first task was being executed, my git commit Agent hook got triggered by a file save and added it to the queue at the end after all the tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted the Agent hook to be executed after every task so that each task is saved in a separate git commit. However that did not work as I anticipated. This is my understanding of how Agent hook must be called.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are early days of the release of Kiro. Will find out more about this feature going forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;debugging-loop&#34;&gt;Debugging loop&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Few times, when I asked it to debug and fix an issue, it fell into a circular debugging loop and it was doing the same changes over and over again for more than ten times. I had to cancel the task and ask it to explain what it was doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This might not be an issue with Kiro per se but I think it is an issue with LLM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;final-note&#34;&gt;Final note&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kiro, Agentic AI IDE from AWS has started on a good note and using Claude 4.0 Sonnet as their model choice might be their genius move.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI Coding IDEs have been the first multi-billion dollar usecase coming out of Generative AI. AWS move to introduce Kiro at this moment in time will surely capture sizable userbase considering you pay 19$ per month to get the industry top LLM for coding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have not tried Kiro, do give it a try. Let me know in comments what is your Kiro experience?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;follow-me&#34;&gt;Follow Me&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are new to my posts, I regularly post about AWS, EKS, Kubernetes and Cloud computing related topics. Do follow me in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vijaykodam/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; and visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.to/vijaykodam&#34;&gt;my dev.to posts&lt;/a&gt;. You can find all my previous blog posts in &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/posts&#34;&gt;my blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Built an AI Agent using Strands Agents SDK</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/built-an-ai-agent/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2025 23:44:09 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/built-an-ai-agent/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/strands.png&#34; alt=&#34;strands&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Built an AI Agent using Strands Agents SDK from Amazon Web Services (AWS) which calls my Kubernetes MCP server. Read more to find out…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;agents-and-mcp&#34;&gt;Agents and MCP&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI Agents and Model Context Protocol are the most popular concepts in Gen AI now. Now I have created an AI Agent which calls MCP server to debug issues in my K8s cluster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I created a Model Context Protocol (MCP) server for &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/vijaykodam/kubernetes-readonly-mcp&#34;&gt;Kubernetes read-only operations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;strands-agents-sdk&#34;&gt;Strands Agents SDK&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AWS has created an SDK for building AI Agents called &lt;a href=&#34;https://strandsagents.com/latest/&#34;&gt;Strands Agents SDK&lt;/a&gt;. Now it added support for MCP as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used Strands Agents SDK and built an AI Agent which calls my K8s MCP server and debugs issues in my running K8s cluster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This demonstrates the AI Agents ability to achieve goals by perceiving the environment, reasoning and acting upon it using available tools like MCP servers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;demo&#34;&gt;Demo&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is my detailed demo of my AI Agent. Links in comments about Strands and my MCP server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe 
   src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/GDEtRssnpx4?si=7S3cvYg-2Bz5PtEa&#34; 
   width=&#34;560&#34; 
   height=&#34;315&#34; 
   title=&#34;Embedded Content&#34; 
   frameborder=&#34;0&#34; 
   allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&#34; 
   referrerpolicy=&#34;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&#34;
   allowfullscreen&gt;
 &lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are you building with Strands Agents SDK?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;follow-me&#34;&gt;Follow Me&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are new to my posts, I regularly post about AWS, EKS, Kubernetes and Cloud computing related topics. Do follow me in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vijaykodam/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; and visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.to/vijaykodam&#34;&gt;my dev.to posts&lt;/a&gt;. You can find all my previous blog posts in &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/posts&#34;&gt;my blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tic Tac Toe</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/projects/tic-tac-toe/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 15:20:07 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/projects/tic-tac-toe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Created it using Google Gemini CLI on 2nd Jul 2025
&lt;link rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/css/tic-tac-toe.css&#34;&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;tic-tac-toe-container&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div id=&#34;game-setup&#34;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&#34;setup-section&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p class=&#34;setup-title&#34;&gt;Game Mode&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;div class=&#34;button-group&#34; id=&#34;game-mode-selector&#34;&gt;
                &lt;button class=&#34;btn-toggle active&#34; data-mode=&#34;pvc&#34;&gt;Player vs. Computer&lt;/button&gt;
                &lt;button class=&#34;btn-toggle&#34; data-mode=&#34;pvp&#34;&gt;Player vs. Player&lt;/button&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&#34;setup-section&#34; id=&#34;first-move-container&#34;&gt;
            &lt;p class=&#34;setup-title&#34;&gt;Who Goes First?&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;div class=&#34;button-group&#34; id=&#34;first-move-selector&#34;&gt;
                &lt;button class=&#34;btn-toggle active&#34; data-first-move=&#34;player&#34;&gt;Player (X)&lt;/button&gt;
                &lt;button class=&#34;btn-toggle&#34; data-first-move=&#34;computer&#34;&gt;Computer (O)&lt;/button&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;button id=&#34;start-game&#34;&gt;Start Game&lt;/button&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id=&#34;game-board&#34; class=&#34;hidden&#34;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&#34;cell&#34; data-index=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&#34;cell&#34; data-index=&#34;1&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&#34;cell&#34; data-index=&#34;2&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&#34;cell&#34; data-index=&#34;3&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&#34;cell&#34; data-index=&#34;4&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&#34;cell&#34; data-index=&#34;5&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&#34;cell&#34; data-index=&#34;6&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&#34;cell&#34; data-index=&#34;7&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&#34;cell&#34; data-index=&#34;8&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id=&#34;message&#34; class=&#34;hidden&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;button id=&#34;restart-game&#34; class=&#34;hidden&#34;&gt;Restart Game&lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/js/tic-tac-toe.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My thoughts on LLM Video Generation</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/llm-video-generation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 22:02:48 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/llm-video-generation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Generated this video using Google Veo3. I realized two things after generating this video &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe 
  src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/PbsennA_HHo?si=SWpMcqVq1ovIjdcl&#34; 
  width=&#34;560&#34; 
  height=&#34;315&#34; 
  title=&#34;Embedded Content&#34; 
  frameborder=&#34;0&#34; 
  allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&#34; 
  referrerpolicy=&#34;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&#34;
  allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;prompt-engineering-is-still-the-king&#34;&gt;Prompt Engineering is still the KING.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As humans we know the world and we fill in the blanks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My prompt for this video was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;A white bread slice lying down on a table. An egg is besides it. Then its hands and legs pop out and it stands up. It picks up the egg. Walks on to the pan on a gas stove beside the table. The bread slice cracks the egg on the pan. Throws the egg shells away. Then jumps on the egg to become french toast.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is normal scenario for us but for a multi-modal LLM which needs frame-by-frame information, this is not enough information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After generating this video, I used ChatGPT to generate a detailed prompt for storyboarding and frame-by-frame detailed information on what happens in that frame. That video was good but it failed for a different reason. That brings me to my second realization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;physics-is-hard-for-llms&#34;&gt;Physics is hard for LLMs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LLMs still struggle with the real-world physics. They are getting better but there is still some more improvement needed until they get really better. See how in the video a set of hands came to lift the bread slice first. Then another set of fingers appeared to crack open the eggs. At the end it didn&amp;rsquo;t become a french toast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the second video I generated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe 
  src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/hFX_Xi5m6gM?si=pcYZmjjeAekABcAM&#34; 
  width=&#34;560&#34; 
  height=&#34;315&#34; 
  title=&#34;Embedded Content&#34; 
  frameborder=&#34;0&#34; 
  allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&#34; 
  referrerpolicy=&#34;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&#34;
  allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See how the bread slice cracks the egg and two butter knobs were thrown and the somehow egg white and yolk dropped from already cracked eggs shells. Also at the end, the bread slice was standing in the pan with two butter knobs. I should have prompted better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the detailed prompt for your reference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;DETAILED MULTI-MODAL VIDEO PROMPT  
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;────────────────────────────────────────
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; · GLOBAL SETTINGS  
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;• Duration ≈ &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;8&lt;/span&gt; s &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;192&lt;/span&gt; frames&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;  
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;• Aspect Ratio / Resolution 16∶9, HD &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1280&lt;/span&gt; × &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;720&lt;/span&gt; px&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;  
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;• Visual Style Bright cartoon-realism; saturated colours; soft morning sunlight &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;key-light &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;40&lt;/span&gt; ° camera-left&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;.  
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;• Camera Single hand-held virtual camera, gentle dolly &amp;amp; pans that keep the bread character centred; f/2.8 depth-of-field.  
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;• Audio Light kitchen ambience bed + spot SFX listed in the storyboard.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;────────────────────────────────────────
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt; · CHARACTER &amp;amp; PROP REFERENCES  
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;| Asset       | Look &amp;amp; Texture                                                        | Size          | Notes |
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;|-------------|-----------------------------------------------------------------------|---------------|-------|
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;| Bread slice | White sandwich bread, 1.5 cm thick, browned crust, cute eyes &amp;amp; mouth; flexible toasted-dough arms/legs ending in white cartoon gloves &amp;amp; red sneakers. | &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;11&lt;/span&gt; × &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;11&lt;/span&gt; cm | Idle breathing motion. |
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;| Egg         | Large ivory hen’s egg with faint speckles; glossy.                    | &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;6&lt;/span&gt; cm tall     | Weighty bounce. |
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;| Pan         | &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;25&lt;/span&gt; cm cast-iron skillet, seasoned black interior, subtle sheen.       | —             | Centered on burner; faint steam once heated. |
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;| Gas stove   | Stainless cook-top, blue flame under pan &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;already lit&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;.               | —             | — |
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;| Table       | Warm oak countertop with visible grain.                               | —             | &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;90&lt;/span&gt; cm from stove. |
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;────────────────────────────────────────
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt; · STORYBOARD &amp;amp; FRAME-BY-FRAME BREAKDOWN &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;8&lt;/span&gt; s &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;192&lt;/span&gt; frames&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;| Timecode &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;s&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; | Camera / Composition                                   | Action &amp;amp; Animation                                               | Key SFX / FX                         | Validation Checks |
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;|--------------|--------------------------------------------------------|------------------------------------------------------------------|--------------------------------------|-------------------|
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;| **0.0 – 0.5** | Static close-up; bread lying flat, egg &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt; cm right.    | Subtle breathing in bread.                                       | Low room tone.                       | ✓ Both assets visible |
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;| **0.5 – 1.0** | Same angle, slight dolly-in.                           | Four limbs pop out with squash-stretch; eyes blink awake.        | &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt; quick “pop” whooshes.              | ✓ Limbs emerge, no overlap errors |
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;| **1.0 – 1.3** | Medium shot; camera tilts up.                          | Bread stands, grabs egg with both hands.                         | Soft thud + cloth rustle.            | ✓ Egg securely held |
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;| **1.3 – 3.0** | Side tracking shot following bread.                   | Bread walks &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;90&lt;/span&gt; cm to stove &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;≈ &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;9&lt;/span&gt; steps at 0.19 s each&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;.           | Sneaker squeaks; faint egg rattle.   | ✓ No foot-slip; egg intact |
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;| **3.0 – 3.5** | Over-shoulder high angle on pan.                       | Bread lifts egg overhead in anticipation.                        | Rising whoosh.                       | ✓ Pan &amp;amp; flame visible |
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;| **3.5 – 4.0** | Two-frame insert on egg striking pan rim.              | Egg cracks; whites/yolk pour in; shells split cleanly.           | Sharp crack → sizzling ramp.         | ✓ No shell bits in yolk |
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;| **4.0 – 4.3** | Return medium; bread flicks shells behind onto table.  | Shells arc back, land out of focus.                              | Light clink.                         | ✓ Disposal path clear |
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;| **4.3 – 4.8** | Low stove-level angle.                                 | Bread crouches; anticipatory squash.                             | Sizzle continues.                    | ✓ Limb IK stable |
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;| **4.8 – 5.3** | Slow-motion &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;0.5 s&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; mid-air front flip; camera up-tilt | Bread leaps &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;15&lt;/span&gt; cm, flips &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;180&lt;/span&gt; °, lands butter-side down on egg.   | “Boing” + louder sizzle on impact.   | ✓ Flip rotation accurate |
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;| **5.3 – 6.5** | Top-down tight shot.                                   | Egg absorbs; bread surface turns golden-brown; steam rises.      | Crackling pops.                      | ✓ Colour shift to &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;#F6B66A |&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;| **6.5 – 7.0** | Pull-back hero shot, slight dolly-out.                 | Bread now French-toast, pats of butter &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; eyes; gives thumbs-up.| Cymbal “ta-da!”                      | ✓ Final pose held &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt; frames |
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;| **7.0 – 8.0** | Freeze-frame hold with gentle vignette.                | Title card optional.                                             | Music sting trails off.              | ✓ All assets on screen |
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;────────────────────────────────────────
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt; · CONTINUITY &amp;amp; TECHNICAL CHECKLIST  
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;1. **Assets present every frame:** bread/toast, pan, stove flame, table.  
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;2. **Lighting continuity:** single key + &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;20&lt;/span&gt; % fill; avoid popping shadows.  
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;3. **Physics:** gravity 9.8 m s⁻²; egg fluid viscosity; no mesh interpenetration.  
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;4. **Animation rules:** limbs ≤ &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;130&lt;/span&gt; % stretch; centre-of-mass forward during walk.  
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;5. **Audio sync:** SFX start within ±2 frames of visuals.  
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;6. **Per-frame metadata required:** camera transform, asset transforms &amp;amp; materials, light vectors, active particles, audio triggers.  
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;7. **Export:** &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;24&lt;/span&gt; fps PNG sequence &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;no alpha&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; + WAV &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;48&lt;/span&gt; kHz 24-bit stereo; master container ProRes &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;422&lt;/span&gt; HQ.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;────────────────────────────────────────
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;END OF PROMPT — ready &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; multi-modal LLM ingestion.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;What is your experience with LLM video generation? Did you try any other LLMs?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are new to my posts, I regularly post about AWS, EKS, Kubernetes and Cloud computing related topics. Do follow me in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vijaykodam/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; and visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.to/vijaykodam&#34;&gt;my dev.to posts&lt;/a&gt;. You can find all my previous blog posts in &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/posts&#34;&gt;my blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Built an app using Lovable, vibecoding startup</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/lovable-app/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 16:29:33 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/lovable-app/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Built a game using &lt;a href=&#34;https://lovable.dev/&#34;&gt;Lovable&lt;/a&gt;, a vibe-coding AI platform, this weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovable organized AI Showdown during the weekend where users can build projects and compete using code-generating AI Models from OpenAI, Anthropic and Google.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of my project, I have created a simple word ladder game, where the player can only change only single letter in each rung to add a valid English word. The game is to change the existing word one letter at a time into the target word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/lovable.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;snowdrop&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the first time I am using Lovable and I am surprised by the maturity of the product. It is very intuitive to use and it creates complete working app in the first prompt itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent 2 hours creating this game, mainly to improve the word list, figure out to build huge amount of valid 3, 4 and 5 letter words, test the functionality, change the UI, check for security issues, change the UX etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anton Osika and team has built an amazing product. Also happy that it is from the Nordics :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feel free to try the game and give me your feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Game URL: &lt;a href=&#34;https://word-ladder.lovable.app/&#34;&gt;https://word-ladder.lovable.app/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are new to my posts, I regularly post about AWS, EKS, Kubernetes and Cloud computing related topics. Do follow me in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vijaykodam/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; and visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.to/vijaykodam&#34;&gt;my dev.to posts&lt;/a&gt;. You can find all my previous blog posts in &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/posts&#34;&gt;my blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Word Ladder</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/projects/word-ladder/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/projects/word-ladder/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Built a game using Lovable, a vibe-coding AI platform, this weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lovable organized AI Showdown during the weekend where users can build projects and compete using code-generating AI Models from OpenAI, Anthropic and Google.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of my project, I have created a simple word ladder game, where the player can only change only single letter in each rung to add a valid English word. The game is to change the existing word one letter at a time into the target word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is an embedded version of the Word Ladder game hosted externally on lovable.app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe
  src=&#34;https://word-ladder.lovable.app/&#34;
  title=&#34;Word Ladder&#34;
  loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
  style=&#34;width: 100%; max-width: 560px; height: 700px; border: 0; display: block; margin: 0 auto;&#34;
  allow=&#34;fullscreen; clipboard-read; clipboard-write; gamepad; cross-origin-isolated&#34;
  referrerpolicy=&#34;no-referrer&#34;
&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align:center; margin-top: 0.75rem;&#34;&gt;
  Having trouble viewing? &lt;a href=&#34;https://word-ladder.lovable.app/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener noreferrer&#34;&gt;Open Word Ladder in a new tab&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- Notes:
- If the external site sets X-Frame-Options: DENY/SAMEORIGIN or a restrictive CSP (frame-ancestors), the iframe won’t render. The page still presents a clear “Open in new tab” fallback.
- Adjust the padding-top above to tune aspect ratio (e.g., 56.25% for 16:9). Current 175% is tall for mobile usability.
--&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Won Amazon Q Coding Challenge</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/won-q-coding-challenge/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 16:33:12 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/won-q-coding-challenge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/amazonq-win.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;amazonqwin&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wow! I won 1st place in the Amazon Q Coding challenge today at AWS Summit Stockholm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had to summon my newfound GenAI vibe coding skills. My experience in working with Amazon Q CLI and Claude Code definitely helped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a python coding challenge with 40 coding exercises starting with easy level and increasing difficulty with each question. You can use Q developer as a vibe coding tool to solve it. Time also matters and I managed to complete all 40 tasks in 35mins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are new to my posts, I regularly post about AWS, EKS, Kubernetes and Cloud computing related topics. Do follow me in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vijaykodam/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; and visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.to/vijaykodam&#34;&gt;my dev.to posts&lt;/a&gt;. You can find all my previous blog posts in &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/posts&#34;&gt;my blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My First Impressions of official EKS MCP Server</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/official-eks-mcp-server/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 01:04:32 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/official-eks-mcp-server/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/eksmcp.png&#34; alt=&#34;eksmcp&#34;&gt;
Image Credits: Generated using ChatGPT 3o&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AWS released official EKS MCP Server today!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have already created &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.to/vijaykodam/building-mcp-server-for-kubernetes-4l10&#34;&gt;my own MCP server&lt;/a&gt; for read-only Kubernetes operations which made me appreciate these four things about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;mcp-tools&#34;&gt;MCP Tools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of one-to-one mapping of K8s CLI commands to EKS MCP Server tools they have created very few tools by combining functionality. For eg, manage_k8s_resource tool manages all K8s resources and supports create, replace, patch, delete, and read Kubernetes operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;manages-eks-clusters&#34;&gt;Manages EKS Clusters&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This EKS MCP Server not only can access your EKS clusters but it can also create and manage new EKS clusters. It creates EKS Auto mode clusters by default. It uses CloudFormation to create new EKS Clusters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;troubleshooting-support&#34;&gt;Troubleshooting support&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Really like how they have given access to LLMs their EKS troubleshooting guide via a tool so that LLM can check AWS in-house knowledge of their experience troubleshooting EKS clusters. The tool name is &amp;ldquo;search_eks_troubleshoot_guide&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;secure&#34;&gt;Secure&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is always important to have least privileged access. Keeping in with that best practice, EKS MCP Server supports read only mode by default. If you are feeling adventurous add &amp;ldquo;&amp;ndash;allow-write&amp;rdquo; option to give write access. This will still block access to sensitive info. There is another option to give access to that as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;final-thoughts&#34;&gt;Final thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creating my own kubernetes MCP server gave me valuable insights into how the MCP server creation is done. This EKS MCP server has simplified MCP tooling, added own knowledge of troubleshooting, added least-privileged option and can create EKS clusters using CloudFormation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;links&#34;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can access the official &lt;a href=&#34;https://awslabs.github.io/mcp/servers/eks-mcp-server/&#34;&gt;EKS MCP server here&lt;/a&gt;. You can read about it in &lt;a href=&#34;https://aws.amazon.com/blogs/containers/accelerating-application-development-with-the-amazon-eks-model-context-protocol-server/&#34;&gt;their Blog post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Really appreciate how EKS MCP server has handled all the functionality really well. Kudos to the EKS team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;follow-me&#34;&gt;Follow Me&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are new to my posts, I regularly post about AWS, EKS, Kubernetes and Cloud computing related topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do follow me in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vijaykodam/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; and visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.to/vijaykodam&#34;&gt;my dev.to posts&lt;/a&gt;. You can find all my previous blog posts in &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/posts&#34;&gt;my blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to get into AWS Community Builders Program</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/how-to-get-into-aws-community-builders/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 22:24:24 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/how-to-get-into-aws-community-builders/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/VijayCommunityBuilder.webp&#34; alt=&#34;VijayCB&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In March 2025, I got into AWS Community Builders Program. Many people reached out to me to know how to get into the program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a detailed article on how to get into AWS Community Builders Program with my own experience thrown in. I hope this is useful to you all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-aws-community-builders-program&#34;&gt;What is AWS Community Builders program&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the official description:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The AWS Community Builders program offers technical resources, education, and networking opportunities to AWS technical enthusiasts and emerging thought leaders who are passionate about sharing knowledge and connecting with the technical community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Official page: &lt;a href=&#34;https://aws.amazon.com/developer/community/community-builders/&#34;&gt;https://aws.amazon.com/developer/community/community-builders/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-do-you-need-to-do&#34;&gt;What do you need to do?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start with the FAQs on the official page. Those have the latest rules and conditions. Read them. Re-read them again. It is important to understand each and everyone of those questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are things you need to do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You must have AWS Builder ID. If you don’t have one then create one at &lt;a href=&#34;https://us-east-1.credentials.signin.aws&#34;&gt;https://us-east-1.credentials.signin.aws&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Join the waitlist for 2026 at &lt;a href=&#34;https://pulse.aws/application/BM2AKLSX?p=0&#34;&gt;https://pulse.aws/application/BM2AKLSX?p=0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The application opens in Jan 2026.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You must have at least two high quality contents created one month before the application opens. This was the condition in 2025, and I guess it will be same in 2026. So make sure you have them ready by Nov 2025.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have purposefully mentioned &lt;strong&gt;two high quality content&lt;/strong&gt; and not an article as there are other mediums as well. You can create Youtube video, write a blog post, talk in local AWS user group, contribute to open source, write a good solution to a question in re:Post. You choose what you want to do. Make sure you have an URL to add in the application which is publicly accessible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AWS wants to hear your original voice and original solution. They are interested in how best you can use AWS technology to build an original solution that solves your problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GenAI makes it trivial generating new content, images, and code.
&lt;strong&gt;DON’T USE GenAI/LLM&lt;/strong&gt; generated text or code in your solution. GenAI generated images are okay if you clearly mention image credits immediately after the image. AWS wants to hear your original thoughts, your own experiences, and how you use AWS to improve the solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One Biggest Tip&lt;/strong&gt; I could give you is: Produce content in your mother tongue if English is not your mother tongue. Use it to your own advantage.
AWS encourages you to produce content in your  own local language. You don’t have to use English. Write in Telugu, Finnish, German, Japanese, Turkish, whatever language you know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are posting on LinkedIn then create content using LinkedIn Articles instead of LinkedIn posts. Posts are temporary. Articles are permanent and are found when you search for topics in or outside of LinkedIn. Also LinkedIn articles supports rich text formatting. Use it to create clear and long content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All your contributions must be publicly accessible and not behind any paywalls. Try opening them in a private incognito browser window and test them before adding the URLs in the application. This way you know those URLs are working fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-experience&#34;&gt;My Experience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my case, I have been working with AWS for nearly ten years and EKS for the last 4-5 years. I always wanted to contribute back to the community. I have run Linux student tech community back in 2002-2005 and I am a big proponent of open source. There was an itch to write and share my learnings from the start. AWS Community Builders program felt like a correct platform for what I wanted to do in my free time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my case, I had written couple of blogs in 2018 and 2020 and there was a big break. I tried to apply for AWS Community Builders program in 2024 and when I opened the application then I came to know that one needs to add link to their two blog posts or other content written in the last one year and those must be created at least one month before the application. I wished I had known about this before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in mid 2024 I wrote couple of posts on my blog and also started actively posting and writing articles in LinkedIn. When the time came in Jan 2025, I applied and luckily got into the AWS Community Builders program.  This year I have written more blog posts than in the last ten years. I am more motivated to share my learnings, help the community and build solutions in the public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;benefits&#34;&gt;Benefits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest benefit of joining AWS Community Builders program for me is the access to the network of like-minded builders and AWS experts. Discussing with them when you are stuck on your solutions, learning from what they build, attending builders-only exclusive sessions from AWS experts are the biggest benefits for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the AWS Swag received as part of the program recently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://dev-to-uploads.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/articles/55dzooha7vwqau6fceeh.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;AWS Swag&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You get some AWS credits for doing proof of concepts or building different solutions using AWS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You also get to post on dedicated organization for builders on dev.to. You get more views and credibility for your posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;final-thoughts&#34;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First and foremost you need to remember that this is a volunteer role. If you are excited to help others learn AWS technologies, share with the world your AWS learnings, and want to write or talk about it then this program is for you. There will be excellent support from AWS in this regard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I personally believe everyone can become an AWS Community Builder if you put the required effort and are willing to help the AWS community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is my way of contributing back to the community by sharing my learnings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;follow-me&#34;&gt;Follow Me&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are new to my posts, I regularly post about AWS, EKS, Kubernetes and Cloud computing related topics. Do follow me in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vijaykodam/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; and visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.to/vijaykodam&#34;&gt;my dev.to posts&lt;/a&gt;. You can find all my previous blog posts in &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/posts&#34;&gt;my blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Built my first MCP Server for Kubernetes</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/building-my-first-mcp-server/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 23:17:36 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/building-my-first-mcp-server/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/first-mcp.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;first-mcp&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;intro&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Built my first MCP Server for read only Kubernetes operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This MCP server was created to provide a secure way to interact with Kubernetes clusters without allowing any create, update, or delete operations. It only exposes read-only APIs to ensure your clusters remain safe while still enabling AI assistants to help you monitor and troubleshoot your Kubernetes resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/vijaykodam/kubernetes-readonly-mcp/&#34;&gt;Github Repo URL&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;model-context-protocol&#34;&gt;Model Context Protocol&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Model Context Protocol (MCP) is an open protocol that standardizes how applications provide context to LLMs. MCP provides a standardized way to connect AI models to different data sources and tools. Read more about it at &lt;a href=&#34;https://modelcontextprotocol.io/&#34;&gt;https://modelcontextprotocol.io/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now all the major companies like OpenAI, Microsoft, AWS and Google adopted it and it has become the industry standard for exposing tools, resources and API endpoints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MCP has been very popular lately and you can see the huge adoption as every company is releasing their official MCP server.
MCP server is the new API endpoint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-yet-another-mcp-server&#34;&gt;Why Yet Another MCP Server?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kubernetes is equally popular and there are many Kubernetes MCP servers out there. Security is still evolving around MCP and I didn’t want to run an MCP server for K8s which can create, update or delete my K8s resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I got an idea to build my own MCP server where only read only operations are part of the MCP servers tools. If there is no capability written to modify then it cannot modify the resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course we could achieve it by creating a restrictive RBAC role in K8s cluster but I wanted to learn and what better way than building your own MCP server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-i-built-it&#34;&gt;How I built it?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have used FastMCP framework for building MCP server. For calling Kubernetes API server, I have used the official Kubernetes Python client. Essentially I was plumbing both those things together and building a solution around them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each API call is created as a separate MCP tool. For example, there is one K8s API call for get pods which has been implemented as get_pods MCP tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a common Kubernetes context initiated once at the start which is shared across the MCP tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;features&#34;&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This MCP server provides the following read-only tools:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;list_pods&lt;/code&gt;: List all pods in a namespace or across all namespaces&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;list_deployments&lt;/code&gt;: List all deployments in a specified namespace&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;list_services&lt;/code&gt;: List all services in a namespace or across all namespaces&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;list_namespaces&lt;/code&gt;: List all namespaces in the cluster&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;get_events&lt;/code&gt;: Get Kubernetes events from the cluster&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;get_pod_logs&lt;/code&gt;: Get logs from a specific pod&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;get_logs&lt;/code&gt;: Get logs from pods, deployments, jobs, or resources matching a label selector&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;todo&#34;&gt;TODO&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Currently I have only implemented the stdio transport. MCP added streamable_http transport recently. For watch or streaming logs such functionality might be needed. I need to check it further.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not all read only Kubernetes APIs are added.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;pypi-package&#34;&gt;PyPi package&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first, for testing purposes, I was calling the MCP server code from a single python file directly. After that added that command in the MCP config file and tested it. Then I thought it would be better if there is a single command to run the python module and after some research decided to build &lt;a href=&#34;https://pypi.org/project/kubernetes-readonly-mcp/&#34;&gt;my own PyPi package&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I only used pip or uv to install python packages and now I got to create one. Now you can install the MCP server using “pip install kubernetes-readonly-mcp@latest”. This was a very fun and learning experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;final-remarks&#34;&gt;Final Remarks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After building, packaging and pushing it to GitHub, I started testing it using VSCode + Cline and installed the MCP server and chat with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project is still in experimental phase. Use it at your own discretion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;demo-video&#34;&gt;Demo Video&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is the demo of installing and usage of my first MCP server for readonly Kubernetes operations. Do let me know what is your experience with MCP?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe 
  src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/bIjzZz7kbDQ?si=fhcs5gvfc44DHr7d&#34; 
  width=&#34;560&#34; 
  height=&#34;315&#34; 
  title=&#34;Embedded Content&#34; 
  frameborder=&#34;0&#34; 
  allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&#34; 
  referrerpolicy=&#34;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&#34;
  allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are new to my posts, I regularly post about AWS, EKS, Kubernetes and Cloud computing related topics. Do follow me in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vijaykodam/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; and visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.to/vijaykodam&#34;&gt;my dev.to posts&lt;/a&gt;. You can find all my previous blog posts in &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/posts&#34;&gt;my blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deploying LLMs on Amazon EKS using NVIDIA GPUs</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/deploying-llm-on-eks-and-nvidia-gpu/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 May 2025 19:43:44 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/deploying-llm-on-eks-and-nvidia-gpu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I have deployed an LLM inference solution on Amazon EKS using NVidia GPU.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of my Generative AI hands-on learning, attended an AWS hands-on workshop, where I have deployed Mistral 7B Instruct v0.3 model using Ray Serve and vLLM on Amazon EKS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;architecture&#34;&gt;Architecture&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is the architecture diagram of the LLM inference solution I deployed on EKS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/llm-on-eks.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;llm-on-eks&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;components-used&#34;&gt;Components used&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to host your own models and control entire lifecycle for security or governance reasons then deploying LLM inference on Amazon EKS is a no-brainer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.ray.io/en/latest/ray-overview/getting-started.html&#34;&gt;Ray&lt;/a&gt; is one of the popular open-source frameworks for building and managing generative AI applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.ray.io/en/latest/serve/index.html&#34;&gt;Ray Serve&lt;/a&gt; is a scalable model serving library for building online inference APIs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.vllm.ai/en/stable/&#34;&gt;vLLM&lt;/a&gt; is a popular high-throughput and memory-efficient inference and serving engine for LLMs. vLLM supports Kubernetes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Used &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ray-project/kuberay&#34;&gt;kuberay operator&lt;/a&gt; for deploying Ray. This operator handles all the complexity for you so I prefer this method for deploying Ray on K8s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.ray.io/en/latest/ray-observability/getting-started.html&#34;&gt;Ray dashboard&lt;/a&gt; provides visibility into overall cluster health, jobs, nodes etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Used &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/open-webui/open-webui&#34;&gt;Open WebUI&lt;/a&gt; for dashboard. Installed NVIDIA Data Center GPU Manager Exporter for monitoring NVIDIA GPU usage in Grafana.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, AFAIK, for getting monitoring data from NVIDIA GPUs you have to install the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/NVIDIA/dcgm-exporter&#34;&gt;NVIDIA DCGM exporter&lt;/a&gt;.  It is straight-forward and exports needed metrics like GPU temperature, GPU Power usage, GPU utilization etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ray, Open WebUI, vLLM, Mistral - All are open source software capable of scaling LLM inference very high. This is an exciting development for open source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;follow-me&#34;&gt;Follow Me&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are new to my posts, I regularly post about AWS, Generative AI, LLMs, MCP, EKS, Kubernetes and Cloud computing related topics. Do follow me in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vijaykodam/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; and visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.to/vijaykodam&#34;&gt;my dev.to posts&lt;/a&gt;. You can find all my previous blog posts in &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/posts&#34;&gt;my blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Generate AWS Arch diagrams using AWS MCP server and Amazon Q CLI</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/mcp-amazon-q-cli/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 May 2025 01:18:22 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/mcp-amazon-q-cli/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently AWS started adopted Model Context Protocol (MCP) and created first set of AWS MCP servers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this blog post, I will show you how to generate entire AWS architecture diagrams using single prompt with this new AWS MCP server and Amazon Q CLI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the generated AWS Architecture diagram:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/aws_data_pipeline.png&#34; alt=&#34;Data pipeline&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read more to find out how …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-mcp&#34;&gt;What is MCP?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Model Context Protocol (MCP) is an open protocol that standardizes how applications provide context to LLMs. MCP provides a standardized way to connect AI models to different data sources and tools. You can read more about MCP from &lt;a href=&#34;https://modelcontextprotocol.io/introduction&#34;&gt;their website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LLMs are essentially text-in-text-out or data-in-data-out systems. Agents or tools give LLMs ability to interact with real world. MCP standardizes the interaction between these agents/tools and the applications, typically via MCP Client on the agent/tool side and MCP server on the application side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MCP has become popular after AWS, OpenAI, Google, and Microsoft decided to adopt the standard making it go to protocol. Now we have lots of open source MCP servers ready to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have tried many MCP Hosts/MCP Clients and Amazon Q CLI is the most simple and straight-forward one. Install Q CLI, login to your AWS Builder ID, and you are good to go on a free tier.
AWS handles the LLM calling transparently. No need of any configurations for LLM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;amazon-q-cli&#34;&gt;Amazon Q CLI&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amazon Q is a generative AI assistant. Recently Amazon Q CLI announced MCP support. This is a big announcement for me as it simplifies using MCP as simple as calling the Amazon Q CLI. I am a terminal guy and have been using generative AI CLI tools like Claude Code and now Amazon Q CLI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;steps-to-install-amazon-q-cli&#34;&gt;Steps to install Amazon Q CLI&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I love about Amazon Q CLI is the installation and usage. Installation is a single command in your Mac.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;brew install amazon-q
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;You must login using either AWS Builder ID or your AWS credentials. Use AWS Builder ID if you are just getting started. This is an easy way to try it using the free tier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;q login
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;And then you just use it by calling:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;q chat
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;architecture&#34;&gt;Architecture&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though we don&amp;rsquo;t interact with LLM directly, Amazon Q CLI uses LLM transparent to the user in the background. Based on the user&amp;rsquo;s query it decides to use the AWS Diagram server via MCP Client inside AWS Q CLI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The MCP Client talks to AWS Diagrams MCP server via Model Context Protocol. Internally it pulls the needs icons, generates diagrams using Python diagrams package DSL. Once the image is generated, Q CLI stores it in the user directory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/mcp-q-cli.png&#34; alt=&#34;MCP Amazon Q CLI diagram&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;prerequisites&#34;&gt;Prerequisites&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Install GraphViz before. See &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.graphviz.org/&#34;&gt;https://www.graphviz.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Mac:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;brew install graphviz
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;demo&#34;&gt;Demo&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this demo I am setting up &lt;a href=&#34;https://awslabs.github.io/mcp/servers/aws-diagram-mcp-server/&#34;&gt;AWS Diagrams MCP server&lt;/a&gt; which is the tool/MCP server which Amazon Q CLI calls to generate AWS architecture diagram.
Watch below demo where I setup the MCP server and generate AWS architecture diagrams using LLM with a single prompt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe 
  src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/HQK5P_Mbp1g?si=LA5Z9swDLv6T7NgP&#34; 
  width=&#34;560&#34; 
  height=&#34;315&#34; 
  title=&#34;Embedded Content&#34; 
  frameborder=&#34;0&#34; 
  allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&#34; 
  referrerpolicy=&#34;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&#34;
  allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are new to my posts, I regularly post about AWS, EKS, Kubernetes and Cloud computing related topics. Do follow me in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vijaykodam/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; and visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.to/vijaykodam&#34;&gt;my dev.to posts&lt;/a&gt;. You can find all my previous blog posts in &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/posts&#34;&gt;my blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Capstone project for Google GenAI course</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/google-genai-capstone-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Apr 2025 00:54:11 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/google-genai-capstone-project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/veggie2.webp&#34; alt=&#34;veggie-recipe-generator&#34;&gt;
Image credit: Generated using GPT-4o.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;how-i-built-generative-ai-agent-for-veg-recipe-generator-with-langgraph-and-gemini&#34;&gt;How I built Generative AI Agent for Veg Recipe generator with LangGraph and Gemini&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-problem-with-finding-best-recipes&#34;&gt;My Problem with finding best recipes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately I have been spending lot of time browsing Internet or youtube cooking videos to find perfect recipe for cooking specific vegetables.
Sometimes I over boil broccoli and sometimes I spend time figuring out how to cook Mexican version of bell peppers dish.
During these times I wonder how great it would be to have a magic tool which could answer my queries directly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-generative-ai-agent-saved-my-day&#34;&gt;How Generative AI agent saved my day?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I took this hands-on &lt;strong&gt;“5-day Gen AI Intensive Course with Google”&lt;/strong&gt; and thought this might be a good way to solve my problem with recipes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the definition from Google’s whitepaper:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Generative AI agents are applications that strive to achieve goals by perceiving their environment and acting upon it using available tools. They extend the capabilities of standalone Generative AI models by integrating reasoning, logic, and access to external information.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To put it simply: LLMs cannot interact with the external world or act  on the external events. GenAI agents use LLMs, reasoning, logic and external tools to achieve the objectives set by the user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This fits perfectly with my personal problem I mentioned about finding recipes. If I set the objective of generating recipes for a given vegetable and if I add tools to get recipes for such vegetables then the GenAI agent will reason about my request, use logic to find the recipes using perfect tool and format it in a human-readable format and present it to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I decided to create a GenAI Agent for Veggie Recipe Generator which helps me with recipes for the vegetables I want. In this capstone project, I have used mock recipes to demonstrate what I have learnt in this course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;demonstrates-three-genai-capabilities&#34;&gt;Demonstrates three GenAI capabilities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project uses Google gemini-2.0-flash API and LangGraph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It will be demonstrating these GenAI capabilities using :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Generative AI agents:&lt;/strong&gt; Using LangGraph to create multi-step conversational flow.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Structured output:&lt;/strong&gt; Making the LLM return information in a predictable human-readable format.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Few-shot prompting:&lt;/strong&gt; Guiding LLM’s behavior with clear examples.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-solution&#34;&gt;The Solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This solution uses an &lt;em&gt;agent&lt;/em&gt; built with LangGraph and powered by Google Gemini API. It follows defined graph to manage the conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It greets the user.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It understands the user&amp;rsquo;s request for a vegetable recipe.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It checks if the vegetable is one it knows (Carrot, Broccoli, etc.).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If valid, it uses a &amp;ldquo;tool&amp;rdquo; (a simulated function) to look up the recipe.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If invalid, it politely informs the user of its limitations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It presents the recipe (if found) in a clear, structured format.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It asks the user if they want another recipe or want to quit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It loops back or exits based on the user&amp;rsquo;s response.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-code&#34;&gt;The Code&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;state-management&#34;&gt;State Management&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LangGraph uses state dictionary to pass between nodes. Here is it’s structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; typing &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; Annotated, List, Literal, TypedDict &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; TypeHint
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; typing_extensions &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; TypedDict
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; langgraph.graph.message &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; add_messages
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; langchain_core.messages &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; BaseMessage
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;### Define the structure for the recipe data returned by the tool&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;Recipe&lt;/span&gt;(TypeHint):
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    title: str
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    ingredients: List[str]
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    instructions: str
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;RecipeState&lt;/span&gt;(TypedDict):
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&amp;#34;&amp;#34;State representing the user&amp;#39;s recipe conversation.&amp;#34;&amp;#34;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    messages: Annotated[List[BaseMessage], add_messages] &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# Conversation history&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    finished: bool &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# Flag to end the conversation&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;guiding-llm-using-few-shot-prompting-and-structured-output&#34;&gt;Guiding LLM using few-shot prompting and structured output&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The core instructions tell the AI its role, limitations, &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to use tools, and crucially, &lt;em&gt;how to format the structured output&lt;/em&gt; it receives from the tool. We include examples (few-shot prompting) to make these instructions clearer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# Snippet from RECIPEBOT_SYSINT&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;RECIPEBOT_SYSINT &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; (
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;system&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;,
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;You are RecipeBot... You can provide recipes ONLY for... Carrot, Broccoli, Spinach, Potato, Bell Pepper.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;\\&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;\\&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;n&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;When the user asks for a recipe... you MUST use the &amp;#39;get_recipe&amp;#39; tool...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;\\&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;n&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;The &amp;#39;get_recipe&amp;#39; tool will return structured information with &amp;#39;title&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;ingredients&amp;#39;, and &amp;#39;instructions&amp;#39;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;\\&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;n&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;When you receive the recipe from the tool, present it clearly to the user in this format:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;\\&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;n&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;Okay, here is a recipe for [Vegetable Name]:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;\\&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;n&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;**[Recipe Title]**&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;\\&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;n&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;Ingredients:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;\\&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;n- [Ingredient 1]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;\\&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;n- [Ingredient 2]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;\\&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;n...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;\\&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;n&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;Instructions:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;\\&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;n [Instructions text]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;\\&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;\\&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;n&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;If the user asks for a vegetable not on the list ..., politely tell them you only have recipes for those listed vegetables, and ask if they want one of those instead.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;\n\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;After providing a recipe... ALWAYS ask the user if they would like another recipe... or if they want to quit.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;\\&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;\\&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;n&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;Example Interactions:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;\\&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;n&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;Human: Can I get a recipe for carrots?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;\\&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;n&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;AI: &amp;lt;tool_call&amp;gt;get_recipe(vegetable=&amp;#39;carrot&amp;#39;)&amp;lt;/tool_call&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;\\&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;n&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;Tool: {&amp;#39;title&amp;#39;: &amp;#39;Simple Roasted Carrots&amp;#39;, &amp;#39;ingredients&amp;#39;: [&amp;#39;1lb chopped carrots&amp;#39;, ...], &amp;#39;instructions&amp;#39;: &amp;#39;Toss chopped carrots...&amp;#39;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;\\&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;n&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;AI: Okay, here is a recipe for Carrot:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;\\&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;n**Simple Roasted Carrots**&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;\\&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;nIngredients:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;\\&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;n- 1lb chopped carrots&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;\\&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;n...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;\\&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;nInstructions:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;\\&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;nToss chopped carrots...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;\\&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;nWould you like another recipe... or would you like to quit?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;\\&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;n&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;Human: Do you have one for Zucchini?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;\\&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;n&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;AI: I&amp;#39;m sorry, I only have recipes for Carrot, Broccoli, Spinach, Potato, and Bell Pepper. Would you like one for those?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;\\&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;n&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# ... more examples ...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;get_recipe-tool&#34;&gt;get_recipe tool&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We define a Python function decorated with LangChain&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;@tool&lt;/code&gt;. This function simulates looking up a recipe and returns it as a structured Python dictionary (&lt;code&gt;Recipe&lt;/code&gt;), not just a block of text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; langchain_core.tools &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; tool
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; typing &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; Dict, Any, Optional
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# Mock Recipe Data (Structured)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;MOCK_RECIPES: Dict[str, Recipe] &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; {
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;carrot&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;: {&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;title&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;Simple Roasted Carrots&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;ingredients&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;: [&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;], &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;instructions&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;...&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;},
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;broccoli&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;: {&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;title&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;Steamed Broccoli with Lemon&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;ingredients&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;: [&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;], &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;instructions&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;...&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;},
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# ... other recipes&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;}
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;@tool&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;get_recipe&lt;/span&gt;(vegetable: str) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; Optional[Recipe]: &lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# Returns structured Recipe or None&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&amp;#34;&amp;#34;Provides a simple structured vegetarian recipe (title, ingredients, instructions) for the specified vegetable. Only works for Carrot, Broccoli, Spinach, Potato, Bell Pepper.&amp;#34;&amp;#34;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    recipe_data &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; MOCK_RECIPES&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;get(vegetable&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;lower())
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; recipe_data:
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; recipe_data
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;:
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;None&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Returning &lt;em&gt;structured output&lt;/em&gt; from the tool allows the chatbot node to reliably extract and format the title, ingredients, and instructions according to the system prompt&amp;rsquo;s rules.
Currently we are returning hardcoded mock data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;building-the-graph-with-langgraph&#34;&gt;Building the graph with LangGraph&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We combine the nodes which perform actions, edges which define flow between the nodes and conditional logic to when to call a tool? or When to quit?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; langgraph.graph &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; StateGraph, START, END
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# --- Build Graph ---&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# print(&amp;#34;Building graph...&amp;#34;) # Debug&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;graph_builder &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; StateGraph(RecipeState)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# Add nodes&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;graph_builder&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;add_node(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;chatbot&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;, chatbot_node)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;graph_builder&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;add_node(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;human&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;, human_node)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;graph_builder&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;add_node(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;tools&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;, tool_node)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# Define entry point&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;graph_builder&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;add_edge(START, &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;chatbot&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# Define edges with conditional routing&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;graph_builder&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;add_conditional_edges(
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;chatbot&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;,
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    route_logic,
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    {
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;tools&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;tools&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;,
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;human&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;human&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;,
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    }
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;graph_builder&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;add_conditional_edges(
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;human&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;,
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    exit_logic,
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    {
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;        &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;chatbot&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;chatbot&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;,
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;        END: END
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    }
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# Tool node always returns to chatbot&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;graph_builder&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;add_edge(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;tools&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;chatbot&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# Compile the graph&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;recipe_graph &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; graph_builder&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;compile()
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;kaggle-notebook&#34;&gt;Kaggle notebook&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to see the code or would like to run it, you can find the jupyter notebook on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/code/vijaykodam/gen-ai-agent-for-veg-recipe-generator&#34;&gt;Kaggle here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feel free to give me your feedback!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;limitations&#34;&gt;Limitations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Currently get_recipes tool uses MOCK_RECIPES dictionary hardcoded. In the future, it would be great to search the Internet or use RAG to search from an embedding vector database.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Limited it to only 5 vegetables to keep it simple. It could be expanded to include list of ingredients and also allergies and some ingredients to avoid.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Current chat box is very basic. It would be great to add voice input.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add more tools to find supermarkets to buy the ingredients.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This capstone project demonstrates how combining the conversational power of Google&amp;rsquo;s Gemini model with the structured workflow capabilities of LangGraph allows for the creation of useful and interactive AI agents. By leveraging &lt;strong&gt;few-shot prompting&lt;/strong&gt; and handling &lt;strong&gt;structured tool outputs&lt;/strong&gt; within an &lt;strong&gt;agentic framework&lt;/strong&gt;, I have solved my recipe issue. There is a lot more one can build with Generative AI Agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;follow-me&#34;&gt;Follow me&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are new to my posts, I regularly post about AWS, EKS, Kubernetes and Cloud computing related topics. Do follow me in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vijaykodam/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; and visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.to/vijaykodam&#34;&gt;my dev.to posts&lt;/a&gt;. You can find all my previous blog posts in &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/posts&#34;&gt;my blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating decibel meter using Claude Code Agentic tool</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/decibel-meter-using-claude-code/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 23:16:20 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/decibel-meter-using-claude-code/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;claude-code&#34;&gt;Claude Code&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Claude Code is an agentic coding tool that lives in your terminal, understands your codebase, and helps you code faster through natural language commands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the last few weeks, I have been experimenting with Claude Code. The more I use, the more I am in awe of this product. It is not perfect but almost there. Works very nicely with small codebase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;idea&#34;&gt;Idea&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I wanted to build a decibel meter app for my kids to know about decibels, how sound is measured and just to give them a new toy to play with. For me, I was already playing with Claude code, the agentic coding toy :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;requirements&#34;&gt;Requirements&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted a simple browser-based decibel meter that uses my device&amp;rsquo;s microphone to measure sound levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;App must use the Web Audio API to access microphone data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am okay with approximate decibel measurements as this will not be calibrated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No data must be stored or transmitted - all processing must happen locally in my browser.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-app-building-process&#34;&gt;My App building process&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Went into my codebase for my blog, opened Claude Code and started prompting to it. After a few revisions the first version was ready in 30 mins and $1.34. It added 560 lines and removed 169 lines in total.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have reviewed the code, tested the functionality. Yesterday I learnt that browsers do not allow microphone access to localhost or HTTP websites. Only HTTPS websites are allowed. I had to copy paste my code into Codepen to test it before pushing into production. After verifying, I had published my project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;cost&#34;&gt;Cost&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like the handy &lt;code&gt;/cost&lt;/code&gt; command to get the amount I burned on this toy project for that session.
You also get the final costs when you exit the claude code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt; /cost
  ⎿  Total cost:            $1.34
     Total duration (API):  5m 5.9s
     Total duration (wall): 36m 57.8s
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;version-1&#34;&gt;Version 1&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is my first version UI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/decibel-v11.webp&#34; alt=&#34;first-version&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;real-world-feedback&#34;&gt;Real World Feedback&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I tested it in my mobile, I realized that the sensitivity for normal voice was very low and the decibel meter was not moving at all. This was not a usable app, if the decibel meter barely moved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now was the time for version 2 of the decibel meter app. With the real world testing I had new set of requirements to make it any useful. Also the decibel meter was showing very tiny fraction for the normal voice range.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;version-2&#34;&gt;Version 2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now for the version 2, based on my testing, real world feedback had a new set of requirements.
The long vertical decibel meter was not usable. So the next way to represent sound was to use a speedometer.
Also the sensitivity should be high so that there is more spectrum for normal voice range and lesser for loud or extremely loud sounds. If there was an option to set microphone sensitivity, then it would be even better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The version 2 took several iterations as old code must be removed and new functionality added. Spent nearly 50 minutes to get it working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;continuous-feedback&#34;&gt;Continuous feedback&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While using Claude code, realized that I was practically testing the app UI after every iteration of code change, checking for errors in console logs, and prompting it to fix those errors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;gotchas&#34;&gt;Gotchas&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One time, I didn&amp;rsquo;t realize the app was using old version of javascript and I thought the app was not working.  Claude Code was trying to fix a non-existent error, happily following my instructions and generating or modifying code continuously. After opening local version in a private window to get rid of cache and cookies, it started working. This could have saved me 15 mins if I had noticed earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So be careful to verify and test properly. Currently, Claude code will generate or modify code if you say it is not working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-final-ui&#34;&gt;The Final UI&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After several iterations and centering the needle, fixing the needle size, colors, shape of speedometer and 50 minutes of my time, got below UI as version 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/decibel-v2.webp&#34; alt=&#34;version2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;decibel-meter-project&#34;&gt;Decibel Meter project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is my &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/projects/decibel-meter/&#34;&gt;Decibel meter project&lt;/a&gt; if you want to try and check it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Note that it is not been calibrated and the values are approximate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No data is stored or transmitted - all processing happens locally in your browser&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;version-2-cost&#34;&gt;Version 2 Cost&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;V2 cost
Total cost:            $2.32
Total duration (API):  12m 14.8s
Total duration (wall): 50m 10.9s
Total code changes:    1373 lines added, 501 lines removed
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-projects&#34;&gt;Other Projects&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I prefer building apps to solve my problems or create apps for my kids to play or learn. These days I am only using Claude Code agentic coding tool. I like working in terminal and Claude code runs entirely in terminal, no IDE, which works perfectly for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have built Cookie consent functionality for my blog. Also built &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/projects/markdown-editor/&#34;&gt;Markdown Editor&lt;/a&gt; to help me while writing my blogs in markdown and &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/projects/snake-game/&#34;&gt;Classic Snake Game&lt;/a&gt;  for my kids to play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these three apps have been built using Claude Code and spent less than an hour to get it published. End-to-end, from ideation to running in the web and using it in my Mobile/Mac.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;final-thoughts&#34;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These days, I started coding or should I say prompting a lot and generating lot of code using Claude Code than before.
I am constantly on the lookout for the next app idea to implement. Building feels great. Seeing end-to-end working solutions feels great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Claude code is not cheap. It is addictive as you literally have a AI coder at your disposal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;your-experience&#34;&gt;Your experience&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How was your experience with Claude Code? Have you used any other agentic coding tools?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;follow-me&#34;&gt;Follow me&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are new to my posts, I regularly post about AWS, EKS, Kubernetes and Cloud computing related topics. Do follow me in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vijaykodam/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; and visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.to/vijaykodam&#34;&gt;my dev.to posts&lt;/a&gt;. You can find all my previous blog posts in &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/posts&#34;&gt;my blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Decibel Meter</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/projects/decibel-meter/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 23:28:14 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/projects/decibel-meter/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Built using Anthropic Claude Code CLI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;decibel-meter-wrapper&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;speedometer-container&#34;&gt;
        
        &lt;div class=&#34;needle-container&#34;&gt;
            &lt;div class=&#34;needle&#34; id=&#34;needle&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;div class=&#34;needle-center&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    
    &lt;div class=&#34;reading&#34; id=&#34;reading&#34;&gt;0 dB&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;description&#34; id=&#34;description&#34;&gt;Please enable microphone&lt;/div&gt;
    
    &lt;button id=&#34;startButton&#34;&gt;Start Measuring&lt;/button&gt;
    
    &lt;div class=&#34;sensitivity-control&#34;&gt;
        &lt;label for=&#34;sensitivity&#34;&gt;Microphone Sensitivity: &lt;span id=&#34;sensitivityValue&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;input type=&#34;range&#34; id=&#34;sensitivity&#34; min=&#34;1&#34; max=&#34;5&#34; step=&#34;0.5&#34; value=&#34;2.0&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    
    &lt;div class=&#34;error&#34; id=&#34;errorMessage&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    
    
    &lt;div class=&#34;child-voice-legend&#34;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&#34;child-voice-title&#34;&gt;Voice Level Guide for Kids&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&#34;voice-level-item&#34;&gt;
            &lt;div class=&#34;voice-level-color&#34; style=&#34;background: #4CAF50;&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;span class=&#34;voice-level-text&#34;&gt;Whisper to Library Voice (0-40 dB)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&#34;voice-level-item&#34;&gt;
            &lt;div class=&#34;voice-level-color&#34; style=&#34;background: #7CB342;&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;span class=&#34;voice-level-text&#34;&gt;Indoor Voice (40-60 dB)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&#34;voice-level-item&#34;&gt;
            &lt;div class=&#34;voice-level-color&#34; style=&#34;background: #FFC107;&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;span class=&#34;voice-level-text&#34;&gt;Classroom Voice (60-70 dB)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&#34;voice-level-item&#34;&gt;
            &lt;div class=&#34;voice-level-color&#34; style=&#34;background: #FF9800;&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;span class=&#34;voice-level-text&#34;&gt;Playground Voice (70-80 dB)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&#34;voice-level-item&#34;&gt;
            &lt;div class=&#34;voice-level-color&#34; style=&#34;background: #FF5722;&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
            &lt;span class=&#34;voice-level-text&#34;&gt;Too Loud! (80+ dB)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/js/decibel-meter.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;link rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/css/decibel-meter.css&#34;&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No data is stored or transmitted - all processing happens locally in your browser.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;dB values are approximate. Calibration has not been done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Markdown Editor</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/projects/markdown-editor/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2025 23:44:00 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/projects/markdown-editor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Generated using Claude Code agentic tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;markdown-editor-container&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;editor-toolbar&#34;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&#34;toolbar-dropdown&#34;&gt;
            &lt;button class=&#34;toolbar-btn dropdown-toggle&#34; title=&#34;Headings&#34;&gt;H&lt;/button&gt;
            &lt;div class=&#34;dropdown-menu&#34;&gt;
                &lt;button class=&#34;toolbar-btn&#34; data-action=&#34;heading1&#34; title=&#34;Heading 1 (# text)&#34; data-tag=&#34;# &#34;&gt;H1&lt;/button&gt;
                &lt;button class=&#34;toolbar-btn&#34; data-action=&#34;heading2&#34; title=&#34;Heading 2 (## text)&#34; data-tag=&#34;## &#34;&gt;H2&lt;/button&gt;
                &lt;button class=&#34;toolbar-btn&#34; data-action=&#34;heading3&#34; title=&#34;Heading 3 (### text)&#34; data-tag=&#34;### &#34;&gt;H3&lt;/button&gt;
                &lt;button class=&#34;toolbar-btn&#34; data-action=&#34;heading4&#34; title=&#34;Heading 4 (#### text)&#34; data-tag=&#34;#### &#34;&gt;H4&lt;/button&gt;
                &lt;button class=&#34;toolbar-btn&#34; data-action=&#34;heading5&#34; title=&#34;Heading 5 (##### text)&#34; data-tag=&#34;##### &#34;&gt;H5&lt;/button&gt;
                &lt;button class=&#34;toolbar-btn&#34; data-action=&#34;heading6&#34; title=&#34;Heading 6 (###### text)&#34; data-tag=&#34;###### &#34;&gt;H6&lt;/button&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;button class=&#34;toolbar-btn&#34; data-action=&#34;bold&#34; title=&#34;Bold (**text**)&#34; data-tag=&#34;**&#34;&gt;B&lt;/button&gt;
        &lt;button class=&#34;toolbar-btn&#34; data-action=&#34;italic&#34; title=&#34;Italic (*text*)&#34; data-tag=&#34;*&#34;&gt;I&lt;/button&gt;
        &lt;button class=&#34;toolbar-btn&#34; data-action=&#34;strikethrough&#34; title=&#34;Strikethrough (~~text~~)&#34; data-tag=&#34;~~&#34;&gt;S&lt;/button&gt;
        &lt;button class=&#34;toolbar-btn&#34; data-action=&#34;link&#34; title=&#34;Link ([text](url))&#34; data-tag=&#34;[](url)&#34;&gt;🔗&lt;/button&gt;
        &lt;button class=&#34;toolbar-btn&#34; data-action=&#34;image&#34; title=&#34;Image (![alt](url))&#34; data-tag=&#34;![alt](url)&#34;&gt;🖼️&lt;/button&gt;
        &lt;div class=&#34;toolbar-dropdown&#34;&gt;
            &lt;button class=&#34;toolbar-btn dropdown-toggle&#34; title=&#34;Code&#34;&gt;📝&lt;/button&gt;
            &lt;div class=&#34;dropdown-menu&#34;&gt;
                &lt;button class=&#34;toolbar-btn&#34; data-action=&#34;code&#34; title=&#34;Inline Code (`code`)&#34; data-tag=&#34;`&#34;&gt;Inline&lt;/button&gt;
                &lt;button class=&#34;toolbar-btn&#34; data-action=&#34;codeblock-js&#34; title=&#34;JavaScript Code Block&#34; data-tag=&#34;```javascript&#34;&gt;JavaScript&lt;/button&gt;
                &lt;button class=&#34;toolbar-btn&#34; data-action=&#34;codeblock-html&#34; title=&#34;HTML Code Block&#34; data-tag=&#34;```html&#34;&gt;HTML&lt;/button&gt;
                &lt;button class=&#34;toolbar-btn&#34; data-action=&#34;codeblock-css&#34; title=&#34;CSS Code Block&#34; data-tag=&#34;```css&#34;&gt;CSS&lt;/button&gt;
                &lt;button class=&#34;toolbar-btn&#34; data-action=&#34;codeblock-python&#34; title=&#34;Python Code Block&#34; data-tag=&#34;```python&#34;&gt;Python&lt;/button&gt;
                &lt;button class=&#34;toolbar-btn&#34; data-action=&#34;codeblock&#34; title=&#34;Code Block&#34; data-tag=&#34;```&#34;&gt;No Language&lt;/button&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;button class=&#34;toolbar-btn&#34; data-action=&#34;blockquote&#34; title=&#34;Blockquote (&gt; text)&#34; data-tag=&#34;&gt; &#34;&gt;❝&lt;/button&gt;
        &lt;div class=&#34;toolbar-dropdown&#34;&gt;
            &lt;button class=&#34;toolbar-btn dropdown-toggle&#34; title=&#34;Lists&#34;&gt;•&lt;/button&gt;
            &lt;div class=&#34;dropdown-menu&#34;&gt;
                &lt;button class=&#34;toolbar-btn&#34; data-action=&#34;unordered-list&#34; title=&#34;Unordered List (- item)&#34; data-tag=&#34;- &#34;&gt;Bullet List&lt;/button&gt;
                &lt;button class=&#34;toolbar-btn&#34; data-action=&#34;ordered-list&#34; title=&#34;Ordered List (1. item)&#34; data-tag=&#34;1. &#34;&gt;Numbered List&lt;/button&gt;
                &lt;button class=&#34;toolbar-btn&#34; data-action=&#34;task-list&#34; title=&#34;Task List (- [ ] task)&#34; data-tag=&#34;- [ ] &#34;&gt;Task List&lt;/button&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;button class=&#34;toolbar-btn&#34; data-action=&#34;hr&#34; title=&#34;Horizontal Rule (---)&#34; data-tag=&#34;---&#34;&gt;―&lt;/button&gt;
        &lt;button class=&#34;toolbar-btn&#34; data-action=&#34;table&#34; title=&#34;Table (| header | header |)&#34;&gt;📊&lt;/button&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;div class=&#34;editor-panels&#34;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&#34;editor-panel&#34;&gt;
            &lt;h3&gt;Markdown&lt;/h3&gt;
            &lt;textarea id=&#34;markdown-input&#34; placeholder=&#34;Type your markdown here...&#34;&gt;&lt;/textarea&gt;
            &lt;div class=&#34;editor-status&#34;&gt;
                &lt;span id=&#34;word-count&#34;&gt;0 words&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span id=&#34;char-count&#34;&gt;0 characters&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span id=&#34;cursor-position&#34;&gt;Line: 1, Column: 1&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&#34;editor-panel&#34;&gt;
            &lt;h3&gt;Preview&lt;/h3&gt;
            &lt;div id=&#34;markdown-preview&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the cost and time it took to create this working code and testing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt; /cost 
  ⎿  Total cost:            $1.01
     Total duration (API):  5m 8.1s
     Total duration (wall): 31m 43.5s
     Total code changes:    713 lines added, 43 lines removed
  ⎿  Set editor mode to vim
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;You just have to have clear requirements and what you want and LLMs are there to make it happen.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Got into AWS Community Builders Program</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/aws-community-builders/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 10:16:35 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/aws-community-builders/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Exciting News!!! I have been accepted into the AWS community Builder Program in the category of Containers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you Jason Dunn for the opportunity and looking forward to contributing for the AWS Community Builders program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Special Thanks to Rajdeep Saha, AWS Community Nordics, Rolf Koski, Petri Rosenström, Prasad Rao, Ashish Prajapati, Parna Mehta, Aritra Nag, Darryl Ruggles, Darya Petrashka, and Saurabh Shrivastava for inspiring me and helping me in my AWS journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/awscommunitybuilder.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;aws&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are new to my posts, I regularly post about AWS, EKS, Kubernetes and Cloud computing related topics. Do follow me in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vijaykodam/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; and visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.to/vijaykodam&#34;&gt;my dev.to posts&lt;/a&gt;. You can find all my previous blog posts in &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/posts&#34;&gt;my blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MLOps 101</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/mlops-101/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 01:53:52 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/mlops-101/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-is-mlops&#34;&gt;What is MLOps?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MLOps&lt;/strong&gt; is set of practices that streamline and automate machine learning workflows. It integrates DevOps practices into machine learning workflows to streamline machine learning operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;why-do-we-need-mlops&#34;&gt;Why do we need MLOps?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the time, as part of the machine learning workflow, they go through EDA, data prep, model training, tuning, then model deployment and monitoring just to find out that it is not ready for production. You have to repeat the process all over again and retrain the model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the machine learning workflows were manual and several teams were involved in this process at different stages, it took lot of time and effort to maintain it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Streamlining and automating such manual process speeds up time to product and decreases manual errors and risks. This leads to scalability of managing and monitoring thousands of machine learning models. This allows the data scientists and engineers to focus on model development and innovation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/mlops-diag.png&#34; alt=&#34;mlops-diagram&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;key-components-of-mlops&#34;&gt;Key components of MLOps&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Machine learning lifecycle has several interconnected stages and all of these key components together make up MLOps. I have been going through various MLOps guides from AWS, Google, IBM and Databricks and realized all of them mostly follow the same key components.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;data-management&#34;&gt;Data Management&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data is the new oil. For ML data makes or breaks a model. It is the backbone of any machine learning model. Fetching right data, storage, preprocessing the data for model development and versioning are very important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Primarily this stage consists of Exploratory Data Analysis (EDA) which includes exploring and understanding data. Data preparation and feature engineering are also part of this step, which includes collecting data, processing data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feature engineering preprocesses raw data into a machine-readable format. It optimizes ML model performance by transforming and selecting relevant features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some MLOps implementations separate EDA and Data preparation into two stages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some of the tools used for data management:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data versioning: Data Version Control (DVC), Delta Lake, MLflow.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data storage and management: Amazon S3, Google cloud storage, Azure Blob storage, Google BigQuery, Amazon RedShift, Snowflake&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data Preparation: Apache Airflow, Databricks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;model-development&#34;&gt;Model Development&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This stage involves the design, training, tuning, and evaluation of machine learning models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some of the tools and services used as part of model development:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Model development frameworks: Tensorflow / Keras, PyTorch, Scikit-learn&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experiment tracking and Management: MLflow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AutoML: Amazon SageMaker Autopilot, Google AutoML, Azure Machine Learning Studio&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IDEs: Jupyter Notebooks, R studio, VS Code, etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;model-deployment&#34;&gt;Model deployment&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Focuses on packaging models, shipping them and deploying them to production environments. This step ensures the model is accessible via an API, microservice or application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the tools and services used for model inferencing, serving and model deployment:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Containers and Orchestration: KServe + Kubernetes platforms like Amazon EKS, GKE, Azure Kubernetes service.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Managed model deployment services: Amazon Sagemaker, Google Vertex AI, Azure Machine Learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Model Serving: Kubeflow, TorchServe, TensorFlow Serving&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;model-inference-and-serving&#34;&gt;Model inference and serving&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Model inference and serving involves making it available for use by applications and end users. It focuses on querying the deployed model to generate predictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Services like Amazon SageMaker Endpoints, Google Vertex AI Endpoints, Azure Machine Learning Endpoints, TensorFlow Serving, KServe and MLflow Models are used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;model-monitoring&#34;&gt;Model Monitoring&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After deployment, continuous monitoring is essential to ensure that models perform as expected and maintain their accuracy over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prometheus + Grafana is the opensource stack for monitoring. Good to get started.
Model monitoring services: AWS SageMaker Model Monitor, Evidently. There are also custom monitoring solutions like Kubeflow pipelines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;governance-and-compliance&#34;&gt;Governance and Compliance&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This key component ensures ML models are developed and deployed responsibly and ethically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Model explainability can be done using Local Interpretable Model-agnostic Explanations (LIME) and SHAP (SHapley Additive exPlanations). MLflow supports Audit and compliance. Amazon Macie handles security. Data and Model Lineage can be done using MLflow, Amazon SageMaker Model Registry and Google Cloud Vertex AI Model Registry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;automated-model-retraining&#34;&gt;Automated model retraining&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Automated model retraining involves retraining the ML model when its performance degrades or when new data becomes available. In this stage model retraining is triggered when specific conditions are met, then retrain the model using latest data and then evaluate the retrained model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the adoption of machine learning is sky rocketing, the importance of MLOps is now higher than ever. MLOps helps automate and streamline machine learning operations. I have tried listing some of the tools used in MLOps is every key component/stage of machine learning workflow. Which tools or services you choose for MLOps depends on whether you are running on AWS, Google, Azure, Databricks, baremetal or opensource. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hope this provided you with a good MLOps overview! What tools and services do you use in your MLOps?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are new to my posts, I regularly post about AWS, AI/ML, EKS, Kubernetes, and Cloud computing related topics. Do follow me in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vijaykodam/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; and visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.to/vijaykodam&#34;&gt;my dev.to posts&lt;/a&gt;. You can find all my previous blog posts in &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/posts&#34;&gt;my blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the references I used to learn and write this blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MLOps from Google from google &lt;a href=&#34;https://cloud.google.com/discover/what-is-mlops&#34;&gt;https://cloud.google.com/discover/what-is-mlops&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MLOps from AWS &lt;a href=&#34;https://aws.amazon.com/what-is/mlops/&#34;&gt;https://aws.amazon.com/what-is/mlops/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MLOps from IBM &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ibm.com/think/topics/mlops&#34;&gt;https://www.ibm.com/think/topics/mlops&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MLOps from Databricks &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.databricks.com/glossary/mlops&#34;&gt;https://www.databricks.com/glossary/mlops&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Practitioners Guide to Machine Learning Operations (MLOps) &lt;a href=&#34;https://cloud.google.com/resources/mlops-whitepaper&#34;&gt;https://cloud.google.com/resources/mlops-whitepaper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pod Disruption Budget vs NodePool Disruption Budget?</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/pod-disruption-budget-vs-nodepool-disruption-budget/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Mar 2025 23:45:23 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/pod-disruption-budget-vs-nodepool-disruption-budget/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In Kubernetes, managing downtimes is very critical to maintain High Availability. &lt;strong&gt;Pod Disruption Budget&lt;/strong&gt; (PDB in short) and &lt;strong&gt;NodePool Disruption Budget&lt;/strong&gt; (NDB in short) plays an important role in managing high availability at different layers of Kubernetes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PDBs ensure that a minimum number of application pods are running when one or more nodes are disrupted voluntarily, for example during cluster upgrades, node drain etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can set pdb value to either &amp;ldquo;&lt;code&gt;minAvailable&lt;/code&gt;&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;&lt;code&gt;maxUnavailable&lt;/code&gt;&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some example usages of PDB:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By setting &amp;ldquo;&lt;code&gt;minAvailable&lt;/code&gt;&amp;rdquo; to quorum size of 3 when scale is 5 for an etcd cluster, you make sure etcd pods do not reduce below quorum thus keeping the writes from failing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you only run single replica of your application pod and you don&amp;rsquo;t want voluntary disruptions to terminate the application then set &amp;ldquo;&lt;code&gt;maxUnavailable=0&lt;/code&gt;&amp;rdquo;.  In this case, you have to manually evict the pod. This allows you to plan for downtime and then delete the pod manually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PDBs help prevent downtime by ensuring enough replicas are running when the nodes are down voluntarily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check the popular statefulsets to see how they have configured pdb in their K8s yamls. Here is one such &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/strimzi/strimzi-kafka-operator/blob/main/install/cluster-operator/040-Crd-kafka.yaml#L3241&#34;&gt;example&lt;/a&gt; from strimzi-kafka-operator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NodePool Disruption Budgets&lt;/strong&gt; (NDB) controls how many nodes in a node pool can be disrupted simultaneously, e.g., during rolling updates, Karpenter autoscaling etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NodePools and NDBs are part of Karpenter and you must have Karpenter installed in your Kubernetes cluster before configuring NDBs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Karpenter uses NDBs to rate limit Karpenter&amp;rsquo;s disruption. If undefined, it defaults to &amp;ldquo;node:10%&amp;rdquo;. NDBs do not prevent Karpenter from terminating  expired nodes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examples of NDB:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;code&gt;spec.disruption.budgets.nodes: 10%&lt;/code&gt;&amp;rdquo; will only allow 10% nodes in that nodepool to be disrupted. You can add reasons like &amp;ldquo;if nodes are Empty&amp;rdquo; along with 10% limit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another example for NDB would be to block node disruption first hour during the day for underutilized nodes using:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;     - nodes: &amp;#34;0&amp;#34;
        schedule: &amp;#34;@daily&amp;#34;
        duration: 1h
        reasons:
        - &amp;#34;Underutilized&amp;#34;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can attach multiple budgets to the same NDB.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Set &amp;ldquo;&lt;code&gt;karpenter.sh/do-not-disrupt: true&lt;/code&gt;&amp;rdquo; to block Karpenter from voluntarily choosing you pod, Deployment, Node or NodePool. Note that setting this annotation does not prevent nodes from forceful disruptions like Expiration, Node Repair etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see in this below diagram, PDB is attached to specific set of pods using a label selector &lt;code&gt;.spec.selector&lt;/code&gt;. You add NDB budget in the NodeClass YAML.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/pdb-ndb-v1.png&#34; alt=&#34;PDB vs NDB&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To summarize, use PDB to maintain availability of critical application pods and use NDB to limit disruptions at nodepool level. By combining both, you can increase your pod availability and cluster stability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you use PDB or NDB? Share your experience in my &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/feed/update/urn:li:activity:7302022325053353984/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn post&lt;/a&gt; comments!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are new to my posts, I regularly post about AWS, EKS, Kubernetes and Cloud computing related topics. Do follow me in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vijaykodam/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; and visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.to/vijaykodam&#34;&gt;my dev.to posts&lt;/a&gt;. You can find all my previous blog posts in &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/posts&#34;&gt;my blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Claude Code Agentic CLI demo</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/claude-code-demo/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 23:58:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/claude-code-demo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/claude-code-shell.png&#34; alt=&#34;claude-code&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is my Day Zero hands-on demo of Claude Code using Claude 3.7 Sonnet. Both were released by Anthropic today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Claude 3.7 Sonnet, is the first hybrid reasoning model on the market by Anthropic. They have also introduced a command line tool for agentic coding, Claude Code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have installed in my mac and tried agentic code and made a demo video for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe 
  src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/mFN-MGEVMMI?si=a_ZpbzvN6GBuacZu&#34; 
  width=&#34;560&#34; 
  height=&#34;315&#34; 
  title=&#34;Embedded Content&#34; 
  frameborder=&#34;0&#34; 
  allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&#34; 
  referrerpolicy=&#34;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&#34;
  allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a look and add in comments how are you planning to use this shiny new agentic code tool in your workflow?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It cost me $0.3273 for 1 minute usage of Anthropic API. It is costly for personal use. That is my personal feeling.
&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/claude-code-cost.png&#34; alt=&#34;claude-code-cost&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would rather want this Claude code like agentic code tool to run locally and call a local llm running on my mac. Everything local, and secure solution. Of course, there will be some opensource tool out in the market in a month doing the same thing. Let&amp;rsquo;s hope so&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you think? Write in comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are new to my posts, I regularly post about AWS, EKS, Kubernetes and Cloud computing related topics. Do follow me in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vijaykodam/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; and visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.to/vijaykodam&#34;&gt;my dev.to posts&lt;/a&gt;. You can find all my previous blog posts in &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/posts&#34;&gt;my blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Classic Snake Game using LLMs</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/snake-game/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2025 23:23:47 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/snake-game/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/SnakeRedApple.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;snake&#34;&gt;
Image Credit: Generated using Google Imagen3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;intro&#34;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last August, I have spent a week trying to create working applications using GenAI models. These were meant to be useful for me and my kids and to assess the capabilities of the then popular LLMs like ChatGPT, Claude, and Gemini. You can find them here &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/projects/&#34;&gt;https://vijay.eu/projects/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-initial-experience&#34;&gt;My initial experience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was my experience back then: Ask each LLM to generate code for a project, copy the code into local files, test it locally, come up with new suggestions and then rinse and repeat until I found the project working well as per my expectation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this exercise I have used: Anthropic Claude, Google Gemini, and OpenAI ChatGPT.
Each had a different way of generating code, handling code changes on top of existing code and updating code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From my experience at that time, Anthropic Claude understood prompts really well and generated code much better than all other LLMs. The quality of code was way better than others. One major advantage was Claude Artifacts. This was a deal breaker for me and game changer for testing quick prototypes in the chat window itself. Also Claude allowed you to host the code and gave you an URL to share with your friends. Getting the html files and testing locally also worked seemlessly. It let you download the files. No copy pasting code from the chat window, which was the case for the remaining two LLMs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;new-challenge&#34;&gt;New Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then came the other challenge. My website(&lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu&#34;&gt;https://vijay.eu&lt;/a&gt;) is based on Hugo and it is a static website hosted on GitHub Pages. GitHub delivers the static webpages to your mobile/computer when you open my website. There is no dynamic content in my website so there is no need of backend server to process the requests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to host my projects created using LLMs also on my website. This means, those projects should be fully static and should not require a backend server to handle any requests for the frontend running in user&amp;rsquo;s mobile or computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hugo uses templating which simplifies adding new posts, which means all posts have the same header, footer, common javascript and common CSS. However for my projects, most of the magic is handled as part of Javascript and CSS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent several hours tweaking the code, explaining this to LLMs and asking them to generate the code which works with my existing hugo code. This took quite an effort and took several trial and errors before the first project worked. When I wanted to create a second flag game I had to do all this over again as it included a different design and there were upto ten questions each coming one after another. I enjoyed building those games but thought these should have been handled automatically for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;current-experience-with-llms&#34;&gt;Current experience with LLMs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Today after four months&lt;/strong&gt;, I wanted to check how far these LLMs have improved. So I decided to create classic snake game for my kids to play. Asked the same prompt to Claude, Gemini and ChatGPT. ChatGPT has new feature similar to Claude&amp;rsquo;s artifact. ChatGPT created the code and displayed the code and demo window. When I pressed Preview, it kinda worked until the green snake (a single green square) ate the first red square. After that it all went haywire. There were multiple red squares appearing randomly across the box and the green square does not move.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gemini generated code in a window and no option to run locally in the window. Copied the code to my computer and ran it locally. It didn&amp;rsquo;t work. There was a black box and nothing else. No red or green squares.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, Claude generated perfectly working code, tested it in the artifact window and also customized the code to work with my hugo website. It also gave me instructions to add shortcodes in my hugo to add new javascript and css for this game. I felt the snake was moving too fast and asked Claude to generate new version to add three different speeds. It did on first try. I have tested it locally then added it my blog and pushed the changes. You can try this snake game on my website at &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/projects/snake-game/&#34;&gt;https://vijay.eu/projects/snake-game/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;winner-this-time&#34;&gt;Winner this time&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, in this second round of my game benchmarking of LLMs, the winner is &lt;strong&gt;Anthropic Claude&lt;/strong&gt; :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-thoughts&#34;&gt;My Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These LLMs are now getting more advanced, producing error free code and understanding user prompts much better. This took me 10 minutes to prompt, test, download and push it to my website. TEN minutes from getting the idea to publishing it live on my website. This is A-W-E-S-O-M-E. You just have to imagine and you have unlimited digital workers, a.k.a LLMs, realizing those dreams for you. Democratizing code for everyone. This gives more power to people who can create end-to-end projects from idea to design to code to deploying it in real world production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How was your experience working with LLMs? What difference have you observed over the last six months?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are new to my posts, I regularly post about AWS, EKS, Kubernetes and Cloud computing related topics. Do follow me in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vijaykodam/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; and visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.to/vijaykodam&#34;&gt;my dev.to posts&lt;/a&gt;. You can find all my previous blog posts in &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/posts&#34;&gt;my blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Classic Snake Game</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/projects/snake-game/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2025 19:58:58 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/projects/snake-game/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;style&gt;
    .game-container {
        display: flex;
        flex-direction: column;
        align-items: center;
        margin: 20px auto;
        max-width: 100%;
    }

    .game-title {
        font-size: 36px;
        font-weight: bold;
        margin-bottom: 20px;
        text-align: center;
        font-family: Arial, sans-serif;
    }

    .speed-selector {
        margin: 10px 0;
        padding: 10px;
        display: flex;
        gap: 10px;
        justify-content: center;
    }

    .speed-btn {
        padding: 8px 16px;
        border: 2px solid #333;
        border-radius: 5px;
        background: white;
        cursor: pointer;
        font-family: Arial, sans-serif;
        transition: all 0.3s ease;
    }

    .speed-btn.active {
        background: #333;
        color: white;
    }

    #gameCanvas {
        border: 2px solid #333;
        background: #f0f0f0;
        max-width: 100%;
        touch-action: none;
    }

    .controls {
        display: none;
        margin-top: 20px;
        touch-action: none;
    }

    @media (max-width: 768px) {
        .controls {
            display: grid;
            grid-template-columns: repeat(3, 1fr);
            gap: 10px;
            width: 200px;
        }

        .control-btn {
            padding: 15px;
            background: #333;
            color: white;
            border: none;
            border-radius: 5px;
            font-size: 18px;
            touch-action: none;
        }

        .control-btn:active {
            background: #555;
        }

        #up { grid-column: 2; grid-row: 1; }
        #left { grid-column: 1; grid-row: 2; }
        #right { grid-column: 3; grid-row: 2; }
        #down { grid-column: 2; grid-row: 3; }
    }

    .score {
        font-size: 24px;
        margin: 10px 0;
        font-family: Arial, sans-serif;
    }

    .game-over {
        display: none;
        position: fixed;
        top: 50%;
        left: 50%;
        transform: translate(-50%, -50%);
        background: rgba(0, 0, 0, 0.8);
        color: white;
        padding: 20px;
        border-radius: 10px;
        text-align: center;
        z-index: 1000;
    }

    .restart-btn {
        margin-top: 10px;
        padding: 10px 20px;
        background: #4CAF50;
        color: white;
        border: none;
        border-radius: 5px;
        cursor: pointer;
    }

    .restart-btn:hover {
        background: #45a049;
    }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;game-container&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;speed-selector&#34;&gt;
        &lt;button class=&#34;speed-btn&#34; data-speed=&#34;slow&#34;&gt;Slow&lt;/button&gt;
        &lt;button class=&#34;speed-btn active&#34; data-speed=&#34;normal&#34;&gt;Normal&lt;/button&gt;
        &lt;button class=&#34;speed-btn&#34; data-speed=&#34;fast&#34;&gt;Fast&lt;/button&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;score&#34;&gt;Score: &lt;span id=&#34;scoreValue&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;canvas id=&#34;gameCanvas&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;400&#34;&gt;&lt;/canvas&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;controls&#34;&gt;
        &lt;button id=&#34;up&#34; class=&#34;control-btn&#34;&gt;↑&lt;/button&gt;
        &lt;button id=&#34;left&#34; class=&#34;control-btn&#34;&gt;←&lt;/button&gt;
        &lt;button id=&#34;right&#34; class=&#34;control-btn&#34;&gt;→&lt;/button&gt;
        &lt;button id=&#34;down&#34; class=&#34;control-btn&#34;&gt;↓&lt;/button&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;game-over&#34; id=&#34;gameOver&#34;&gt;
        &lt;h2&gt;Game Over!&lt;/h2&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Final Score: &lt;span id=&#34;finalScore&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;button class=&#34;restart-btn&#34; onclick=&#34;restartGame()&#34;&gt;Play Again&lt;/button&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This classic snake game has been created using Anthropic Claude in a single prompt on 16 Feb 2025. Documenting it for future reference to track the speed of development in GenAI/LLMs. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
    (function() {
        const canvas = document.getElementById(&#39;gameCanvas&#39;);
        const ctx = canvas.getContext(&#39;2d&#39;);
        const scoreElement = document.getElementById(&#39;scoreValue&#39;);
        const finalScoreElement = document.getElementById(&#39;finalScore&#39;);
        const gameOverElement = document.getElementById(&#39;gameOver&#39;);
        const speedButtons = document.querySelectorAll(&#39;.speed-btn&#39;);

        const gridSize = 20;
        const tileCount = canvas.width / gridSize;

        let snake = [{ x: 10, y: 10 }];
        let food = { x: 15, y: 15 };
        let dx = 0;
        let dy = 0;
        let score = 0;
        let gameLoop;
        
        const speeds = {
            slow: 150,
            normal: 100,
            fast: 70
        };
        let currentSpeed = speeds.normal;
        let baseSpeed = speeds.normal;

        function setSpeed(speedType) {
            baseSpeed = speeds[speedType];
            currentSpeed = baseSpeed;
            if (gameLoop) {
                clearInterval(gameLoop);
                gameLoop = setInterval(drawGame, currentSpeed);
            }
            
            speedButtons.forEach(btn =&gt; {
                btn.classList.remove(&#39;active&#39;);
                if (btn.dataset.speed === speedType) {
                    btn.classList.add(&#39;active&#39;);
                }
            });
        }

        speedButtons.forEach(button =&gt; {
            button.addEventListener(&#39;click&#39;, () =&gt; {
                setSpeed(button.dataset.speed);
            });
        });

        function drawGame() {
            clearCanvas();
            moveSnake();
            checkCollision();
            drawFood();
            drawSnake();
        }

        function clearCanvas() {
            ctx.fillStyle = &#39;#f0f0f0&#39;;
            ctx.fillRect(0, 0, canvas.width, canvas.height);
        }

        function drawSnake() {
            ctx.fillStyle = &#39;#4CAF50&#39;;
            snake.forEach(segment =&gt; {
                ctx.fillRect(segment.x * gridSize, segment.y * gridSize, gridSize - 2, gridSize - 2);
            });
        }

        function drawFood() {
            ctx.fillStyle = &#39;#FF0000&#39;;
            ctx.fillRect(food.x * gridSize, food.y * gridSize, gridSize - 2, gridSize - 2);
        }

        function moveSnake() {
            const head = { x: snake[0].x + dx, y: snake[0].y + dy };
            snake.unshift(head);

            if (head.x === food.x &amp;&amp; head.y === food.y) {
                score += 10;
                scoreElement.textContent = score;
                generateFood();
                increaseSpeed();
            } else {
                snake.pop();
            }
        }

        function generateFood() {
            food = {
                x: Math.floor(Math.random() * tileCount),
                y: Math.floor(Math.random() * tileCount)
            };
            if (snake.some(segment =&gt; segment.x === food.x &amp;&amp; segment.y === food.y)) {
                generateFood();
            }
        }

        function checkCollision() {
            const head = snake[0];

            if (head.x &lt; 0 || head.x &gt;= tileCount || head.y &lt; 0 || head.y &gt;= tileCount) {
                gameOver();
            }

            for (let i = 1; i &lt; snake.length; i++) {
                if (head.x === snake[i].x &amp;&amp; head.y === snake[i].y) {
                    gameOver();
                }
            }
        }

        function gameOver() {
            clearInterval(gameLoop);
            finalScoreElement.textContent = score;
            gameOverElement.style.display = &#39;block&#39;;
        }

        window.restartGame = function() {
            snake = [{ x: 10, y: 10 }];
            food = { x: 15, y: 15 };
            dx = 0;
            dy = 0;
            score = 0;
            currentSpeed = baseSpeed;
            scoreElement.textContent = &#39;0&#39;;
            gameOverElement.style.display = &#39;none&#39;;
            gameLoop = setInterval(drawGame, currentSpeed);
        }

        function increaseSpeed() {
            if (currentSpeed &gt; baseSpeed * 0.5) {
                clearInterval(gameLoop);
                currentSpeed -= 2;
                gameLoop = setInterval(drawGame, currentSpeed);
            }
        }

        document.addEventListener(&#39;keydown&#39;, (event) =&gt; {
            switch(event.key) {
                case &#39;ArrowUp&#39;:
                    if (dy === 0) { dx = 0; dy = -1; }
                    break;
                case &#39;ArrowDown&#39;:
                    if (dy === 0) { dx = 0; dy = 1; }
                    break;
                case &#39;ArrowLeft&#39;:
                    if (dx === 0) { dx = -1; dy = 0; }
                    break;
                case &#39;ArrowRight&#39;:
                    if (dx === 0) { dx = 1; dy = 0; }
                    break;
            }
        });

        const controlButtons = document.querySelectorAll(&#39;.control-btn&#39;);
        controlButtons.forEach(button =&gt; {
            button.addEventListener(&#39;touchstart&#39;, (e) =&gt; {
                e.preventDefault();
                switch(button.id) {
                    case &#39;up&#39;:
                        if (dy === 0) { dx = 0; dy = -1; }
                        break;
                    case &#39;down&#39;:
                        if (dy === 0) { dx = 0; dy = 1; }
                        break;
                    case &#39;left&#39;:
                        if (dx === 0) { dx = -1; dy = 0; }
                        break;
                    case &#39;right&#39;:
                        if (dx === 0) { dx = 1; dy = 0; }
                        break;
                }
            });
        });

        gameLoop = setInterval(drawGame, currentSpeed);
    })();
&lt;/script&gt;


</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hands-on Bedrock Agents workshop</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/bedrock-agents-workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2025 00:22:33 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/bedrock-agents-workshop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Are agents the missing piece for LLMs to super-charge real-world adoption? Today, I had the opportunity to attend AWS Immersion Day at AWS Helsinki office and try hands-on workshop on Agents, RAG, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/bedrock-ws-1.webp&#34; alt=&#34;bedrock-workshop&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks Amazon Web Services (AWS), Ankit Nigam, Kimmo Isosomppi, Heidi Tähtinen, Ezaldeen Arafat for organizing this workshop. This was immensely useful and improved my understanding of Agents, RAG, Guardrails and inference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of the hands-on workshop, I have created a mortage-processing-agent which uses RAG to add domain specific knowledge base and then created agents which can determine if end-user can afford it based on their financial situation.
After that, created Amazon Bedrock Flows that orchestrates entire workflow. Last but not the least, created Guardrails to implement safeguards and enforce responsible AI policies for my GenAI application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the mortgage processing agent I built during the hands-on workshop.
The highlighted yellow box is the prompt user enters followed by the response from Bedrock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/bedrock-ws-handson.webp&#34; alt=&#34;bedrock-handson&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, this was a very good way to get hands-on experience on Amazon Bedrock Agents, RAG, Flows and Guardrails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/bedrock-ws-agents.webp&#34; alt=&#34;bedrock-agents&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are new to my posts, I regularly post about AWS, EKS, Kubernetes and Cloud computing related topics. Do follow me in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vijaykodam/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; and visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.to/vijaykodam&#34;&gt;my dev.to posts&lt;/a&gt;. You can find all my previous blog posts in &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/posts&#34;&gt;my blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presented on EKS Auto Mode at the AWS Helsinki Meetup</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/presented-at-aws-meetup/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2025 20:17:49 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/presented-at-aws-meetup/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/aws-meetup-1.webp&#34; alt=&#34;AWS Meetup Presenting&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Had an amazing time presenting at the AWS meetup today! It was great to share my insights on how EKS Auto mode can help the customers get rid off undifferentiated heavy lifting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Started with the basics of Kubernetes for those new to it and then went on to explain how EKS helps customers and how EKS Auto mode will simplify K8s Day 2 operations. The lively Q&amp;amp;A was a highlight, and I learned a lot from the audience&amp;rsquo;s perspectives.  Public speaking is a journey, and I&amp;rsquo;m grateful for the opportunity to practice and grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A huge thank you to Petri Rosenström, Rolf Koski and Accenture for organizing the Amazon Web Services (AWS) meetup today in Helsinki.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also learnt about Accenture&amp;rsquo;s technology vision from Juha Takala, Emil Nyback and interesting GenAI talk from Niklas Liljestrand !!! All great talks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/aws-meetup-2.webp&#34; alt=&#34;AWS Meetup Presenting 2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are new to my posts, I regularly post about AWS, EKS, Kubernetes and Cloud computing related topics. Do follow me in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vijaykodam/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; and visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.to/vijaykodam&#34;&gt;my dev.to posts&lt;/a&gt;. You can find all my previous blog posts in &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/posts&#34;&gt;my blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Running Deepseek R1 locally</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/running-deepseek-locally/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 22:12:06 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/running-deepseek-locally/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/snowdrop.webp&#34; alt=&#34;snowdrop&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a video of Deepseek R1 running locally on my Macbook.
Now that everyone is amazed by the low level of resource utilization and open weight model of Deepseek R1, installed 8B model locally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the help of ollama it is as simple as running a single command -
&amp;ldquo;ollama run deepseek-r1:8b&amp;rdquo;
You get your own private, local LLM running securely in your computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My prompt is &amp;ldquo;Generate a five line fairy tale about AI?&amp;rdquo;. In the video, you can see how before generating the response, it thinks. Thinking text is in between &lt;think&gt; and &lt;/think&gt; tags.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch the video to read the five line fairy tale about AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you have any experience running Deepseek R1?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe 
  src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/CYfpgvsTG9E?si=QKfJcJB1vjJIRWwe&#34; 
  width=&#34;560&#34; 
  height=&#34;315&#34; 
  title=&#34;Embedded Content&#34; 
  frameborder=&#34;0&#34; 
  allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&#34; 
  referrerpolicy=&#34;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&#34;
  allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are new to my posts, I regularly post about AWS, EKS, Kubernetes and Cloud computing related topics. Do follow me in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vijaykodam/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; and visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.to/vijaykodam&#34;&gt;my dev.to posts&lt;/a&gt;. You can find all my previous blog posts in &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/posts&#34;&gt;my blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New metric to measure the efficiency of AI models</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/new-llm-metric/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 20:03:20 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/new-llm-metric/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, how cheaply and energy efficiently can you generate tokens matters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;Tokens per watt per dollar&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo; metric mentioned by Satya Nadella, CEO of Microsoft, is trying to achieve the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will be a metric by which every LLM is going to be benchmarked against. This is the metric which will showcase how long can an AI investment lasts and how much is your profitability of AI startups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There will be a comparison of LLMs with &amp;ldquo;Tokens per watt per dollar&amp;rdquo; soon, if not already existing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would love to hear your thoughts on this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/posts/satyanadella_wef25-activity-7287900710770196480-7mn6/&#34;&gt;related post&lt;/a&gt; by Satya.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have not already watched, highly recommend Satya Nadella&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kOkDTvsUuWA&amp;amp;t=156s&#34;&gt;AI Tour Keynote: London&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are new to my posts, I regularly post about AWS, EKS, Kubernetes and Cloud computing related topics. Do follow me in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vijaykodam/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; and visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.to/vijaykodam&#34;&gt;my dev.to posts&lt;/a&gt;. You can find all my previous blog posts in &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/posts&#34;&gt;my blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This new EventBridge capability simplifies your cross-account deployments</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/eventbridge-new-capability/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 12:12:42 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/eventbridge-new-capability/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This new capability in &lt;strong&gt;EventBridge&lt;/strong&gt; is going to simplify your cross-account &lt;strong&gt;Event Driven Architecture&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AWS introduced cross account targets for EventBridge event buses today. Now you can add &lt;strong&gt;SQS&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Lambda&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;SNS&lt;/strong&gt; as targets from a different account. Previously only EventBridge in another account could be added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The architecture diagram from the AWS blog is attached in this post. It perfectly captures everything you need to know about this feature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/eventbridge1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;AWS Event Bridge&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember to do these two things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add relevant execution &amp;ldquo;role&amp;rdquo; in source AWS account EventBridge rule.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apply &amp;ldquo;resource policy&amp;rdquo; to SQS/SNS/Lambda in the Target Account.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Role&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; for Source Account and &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Resource policy&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; for Target account. Everything else is same as before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This makes sure security is taken care from both Source and Target AWS accounts and avoids any abuse or DDoS situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read the AWS Blog &lt;a href=&#34;https://aws.amazon.com/blogs/compute/introducing-cross-account-targets-for-amazon-eventbridge-event-buses/&#34;&gt;post here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are new to my posts, I regularly post about AWS, EKS, Kubernetes and Cloud computing related topics. Do follow me in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vijaykodam/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; and visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.to/vijaykodam&#34;&gt;my dev.to posts&lt;/a&gt;. You can find all my previous blog posts in &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/posts&#34;&gt;my blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Surprising side effect of running EKS Auto Mode</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/surprising-side-effect-eks-auto/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2025 12:10:31 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/surprising-side-effect-eks-auto/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One surprising side effect you will notice when you move to EKS Auto mode is that you cannot create a Classic Load Balancer (CLB) using Kubernetes Service annotations. You can only create Network Load Balancers (NLB) using K8s Service annotations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This restriction came into place due to the automatic inclusion of AWS Load Balancer controller as an add-on in EKS Auto mode. AFAIK, there is no way to disable or remove that add-on from EKS Auto mode cluster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are utilizing other ingress controllers like HAProxy, then you cannot create a CLB (HTTPS) using Service annotations. You can only create NLBs using Service annotations and route the traffic through HAProxy ingress controller. After that you can create ingresses which can utilize HAProxy as ingress controller.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means that if you have been using HAProxy ingress controller or other similar ingress controllers then this limitation restricts you to service HTTP/HTTPS traffic through them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since this is a new release, I haven&amp;rsquo;t seen any update in their docs. I am curious on how other ingress controllers handle this change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you faced this issue in EKS Auto mode? Did you manage to fix it? I would like to know your thoughts on this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are new to my posts, I regularly post about AWS, EKS, Kubernetes and Cloud computing related topics. Do follow me in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vijaykodam/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; and visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.to/vijaykodam&#34;&gt;my dev.to posts&lt;/a&gt;. You can find all my previous blog posts in &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/posts&#34;&gt;my blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to pique kid&#39;s interest in computers?</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/teaching-kids-computers/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 12:01:43 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/teaching-kids-computers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/kids-computers.webp&#34; alt=&#34;my-laptop&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last weekend, I wanted to teach my kids how computers work. Instead of just explaining concepts, I decided to make it hands-on. I opened up my laptop and showed them its internals—the motherboard, CPU, RAM, hard drive, battery, speakers and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their eyes lit up as they saw how all the parts come together to create the magic we interact with daily. We talked about where does the laptop get its power from, where does the music come from, how data is stored, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moments like these remind me of the power of curiosity and how early exposure to technology can spark lifelong interests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve ever shared your knowledge with the younger generation, I’d love to hear your experiences. How do you make learning about tech fun and engaging for kids?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Image taken by me. Pictured is my personal laptop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are new to my posts, I regularly post about AWS, EKS, Kubernetes and Cloud computing related topics. Do follow me in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vijaykodam/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; and visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.to/vijaykodam&#34;&gt;my dev.to posts&lt;/a&gt;. You can find all my previous blog posts in &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/posts&#34;&gt;my blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Have you seen multi-session support enabled in your AWS Console?</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/multi-sessions-in-aws-console/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 11:47:06 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/multi-sessions-in-aws-console/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/multisess.png&#34; alt=&#34;multisession&#34;&gt;
Image: Image shows the multi-session support enabled in my AWS Console.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Observed it today morning that multi-session support is enabled in my AWS account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This feature saves lot of effort and time for me. I work with different AWS accounts and logging into those AWS consoles or switching between them is an extra step. Usually I use different browsers to keep both AWS console logins active but it increases CPU/memory load on my PC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I can use single browser and login to two different accounts simultaneously. Saves CPU/RAM in my PC as I don&amp;rsquo;t have to run two browsers now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AWS manages this by adding unique account specific URLs to identify which account you are in even though you access the same EC2 or EKS service in both accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a big feature for me from usability perspective. Currently this is being rolled out and is available only for limited number of user accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch out for this feature in your AWS account and give it a try!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are new to my posts, I regularly post about AWS, EKS, Kubernetes and Cloud computing related topics. Do follow me in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vijaykodam/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; and visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.to/vijaykodam&#34;&gt;my dev.to posts&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Do you run your database on Kubernetes?</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/database-on-kubernetes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 11:34:54 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/database-on-kubernetes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/dbink8s.webp&#34; alt=&#34;dbink8s&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you run your database on Kubernetes? This has been an evergreen debate. Where does it stand now?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kubernetes has come a long way from running only stateless workloads early on to now supporting statefulsets with improvements in sticky identity, persistent storage and unique network identity. Kubernetes has democratized the container orchestration and given the world tools to run most software at scale. This is only one part of the solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Databases built to run directly on servers or virtual machines have different features to make them highly available, resilient and scalable. Now if you bring those databases and run them on Kubernetes then it is a recipe for disaster. In the recent years, there have been cloud native databases built to run on Kubernetes. This is the remaining part of the solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have a container orchestrator platform like Kubernetes which runs most of your software and now with cloud-native databases, you can run them on Kubernetes too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Best of both worlds? What about latency? How do you handle frequent k8s release upgrades every three months? Now with EKS Auto mode, the worker nodes max lifetime is just 21 days. Imagine moving around your database nodes every two-three weeks? Is it recommended in production? Do you instead use managed database service from hashtag#AWS hashtag#GoogleCloud or hashtag#Azure?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no right or wrong answer and &amp;ldquo;It Depends&amp;rdquo; on the software architecture and business constraints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to hear from you all. Write your opinion in the comments below. Do you run your database on Kubernetes? Why? Why not? What are your reasons? Are you using it in production? What is the adoption for such databases?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are new to my posts, I regularly post about AWS, EKS, Kubernetes and Cloud computing related topics. Do follow me in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vijaykodam/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; and visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://dev.to/vijaykodam&#34;&gt;my dev.to posts&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Image generated using DALL.E to depict storage in the cloud.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is ARC Zonal shift feature in EKS?</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/eks-arc-zonal-shift/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 01:04:17 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/eks-arc-zonal-shift/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/snowdrop.webp&#34; alt=&#34;snowdrop&#34;&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Image Credits:&lt;/em&gt; Generated using DALL.E. &lt;em&gt;This image depicts &lt;strong&gt;resiliency&lt;/strong&gt; in nature similar to what is expected from your AWS architecture :)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I have created an EKS Auto mode cluster and observed that &lt;strong&gt;“ARC Zonal shift”&lt;/strong&gt; feature was enabled for my EKS cluster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amazon Application Recovery Controller (ARC)&lt;/strong&gt; helps simplify and automate recovery for highly available applications. It was initially known as “Route 53 ARC” and since then has expanded to support Amazon EC2 Auto scaling groups, ALB, NLB and now EKS. So it is now just Amazon ARC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can recover from an impaired Availability Zone (AZ) using ARC Zonal Shift and Zonal autoshift. Zonal shift is used when you manually trigger it to shift traffic away from an impaired AZ. Use Zonal autoshift to let AWS monitor and shift traffic on your behalf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to run resilient and highly available applications across multi-AZs in EKS and you want to survive an AZ going down then this is the feature (EKS Zonal Shift) you need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember that this will only redirect internal east-west traffic inside your EKS traffic between your pods. If you want to redirect traffic from loadbalancers similarly then you have to enable an ALB or NLB with ARC Zonal shift.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Performing a zonal shift enables you to achieve rapid recovery from application failures in a single Availability Zone (AZ). This is helpful to build resilience in case of an AZ impairment or when an AZ is down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can enable it from EKS cluster creation step or enable it afterwards for already running clusters. If you are creating EKS auto mode cluster with “Quick configuration” option then ARC Zonal shift is enabled by default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With zonal shift, you can temporarily mitigate issues and incidents by triggering a shift and redirecting in-cluster network traffic to a healthy AZ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this to work, you should already be running EKS worker nodes in multiple AZs (at least three) for HA and resiliency and your applications are already running in multiple AZs. So if your application is already running in three different AZs and if one AZ is impaired then Zonal shift will redirect traffic away from impaired AZ to healthy AZs. In this case, you will have your application running in two AZs as highly available after the third one went down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ideally such setup comes with cost so use it for highly critical workloads where you need such level of high-availability and resiliency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check the EKS Zonal shift documentation to learn more: &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.aws.amazon.com/eks/latest/userguide/zone-shift.html&#34;&gt;https://docs.aws.amazon.com/eks/latest/userguide/zone-shift.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow me on LinkedIn for more content related to Kubernetes, EKS and AWS in general. Visit my website at &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/posts&#34;&gt;https://vijay.eu/posts&lt;/a&gt; for all my posts in one place.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Do you know that EKS Auto Mode enforces a 21-day maximum node lifetime?</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/eks-auto-max-node-lifetime/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 14:13:02 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/eks-auto-max-node-lifetime/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/EKS-Auto-Mode.webp&#34; alt=&#34;Kubernetes&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you know that EKS Auto Mode enforces a 21-day maximum node lifetime?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EKS Auto mode cluster manages worker nodes on your behalf.
Karpenter deletes worker nodes in EKS auto mode nodepools after 21 days of node lifetime. This is the maximum node lifetime. It will be replaced with a new node.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is needed for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;providing security patches&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OS updates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;component upgrades&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improves security posture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-if-you-want-to-modify-the-maximum-node-lifetime&#34;&gt;What if you want to modify the maximum node lifetime?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can reduce the maximum node lifetime by creating a custom NodePool with “spec.template.spec.expireAfter” with a value of node lifetime in hours. Max is 21 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-disable-it&#34;&gt;How to disable it?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If for some reason, you do not want to delete worker nodes so frequent or if you want to keep the nodes static then you can create a new Managed Node Group and add nodes in it.
You can create both EKS Auto mode nodepools and Managed Node groups (without auto mode) in the same EKS cluster. These are called mixed-mode clusters.
I will be covering more about mixed-mode clusters in future posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more insights on EKS, AWS, Kubernetes, and Cloud Architecture, follow me in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vijaykodam/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; and check out &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/posts&#34;&gt;my blog&lt;/a&gt; for all my blog posts in one place.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First Impressions of EKS Auto Mode – A Game Changer!</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/eks-auto-first-impressions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 23:13:15 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/eks-auto-first-impressions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/aws-eks-pic.png&#34; alt=&#34;Kubernetes&#34;&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Image Credit: From AWS EKS Blog&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are my thoughts after initial few days of using &lt;strong&gt;EKS Auto mode&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AWS has truly raised the bar with EKS Auto Mode, a new feature announced at &lt;strong&gt;re:Invent 2024&lt;/strong&gt;. This innovation automates much of the undifferentiated heavy lifting, allowing customers to focus on what matters most: building great applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-hands-on-experience&#34;&gt;My Hands-On Experience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I set up an EKS Auto Mode cluster from scratch and was pleasantly surprised by how much AWS now handles post-installation. You can read in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/how-create-eks-auto-mode-cluster-vijay-kumar-kodam-oqw4f/&#34;&gt;more detail about it here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me break down what &lt;em&gt;Day 2 operations&lt;/em&gt; typically involve:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Managed Node Groups&lt;/strong&gt;: Create managed node groups and wait for worker nodes to come up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EKS Node capabilities&lt;/strong&gt;: Most of them were running as Kubernetes Daemonsets on worker nodes before. Now they run as system processes managed by AWS. This includes components such as service discovery, service load balancing, pod networking, block storage, and credential vending.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Add-Ons Installation&lt;/strong&gt;: Select and install versions for multiple EKS add-ons (latest, standard, or older). Like coredns, EBS CSI driver, CNI driver, EKS pod identity etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Load Balancer Controller&lt;/strong&gt;: Install the AWS Load Balancer Controller for ingress traffic handling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cost Optimization&lt;/strong&gt;: Install Karpenter to manage pod bin-packing, scale nodes dynamically, and select cost-efficient EC2 instances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OS Security patching&lt;/strong&gt;: Address OS security vulnerabilities identified by AWS Security Hub.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cluster Upgrades&lt;/strong&gt;: Over time, you need to upgrade Kubernetes control plane versions and meticulously plan worker node updates. This is a continuous process every 3-6 months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, imagine all these tasks being automated by AWS. That’s EKS Auto Mode for you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;key-highlights-from-my-testing&#34;&gt;Key Highlights from My Testing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No Idle Nodes&lt;/strong&gt;: When I launched my first EKS Auto Mode cluster, there were no worker nodes running initially—just built-in &amp;ldquo;general-purpose&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;system&amp;rdquo; node pools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dynamic Scaling&lt;/strong&gt;: After deploying my first application, Karpenter automatically spun up a worker node tailored to the app&amp;rsquo;s resource requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cost Efficiency&lt;/strong&gt;: Upon deleting the application, Karpenter scaled down the node, saving money by avoiding idle resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This level of automation simplifies cluster operations and significantly reduces costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;pricing-update&#34;&gt;Pricing Update&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EKS Auto Mode introduces a pay-as-you-go control plane pricing model based on the number of EC2 worker nodes, a shift from the flat fee for the standard EKS control plane. While it’s a slight increase in cost, the time and effort saved make it a Win-Win for both AWS and customers. Find more about &lt;a href=&#34;https://aws.amazon.com/eks/pricing/&#34;&gt;EKS Auto mode pricing here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;whats-next&#34;&gt;What’s Next?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/feed/update/urn:li:activity:7269311743338663936/&#34;&gt;created a demo video&lt;/a&gt; showcasing EKS Auto Mode in action. If you’re curious, I highly recommend giving this feature a try!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more insights on EKS, AWS, Kubernetes, and Cloud Architecture, follow me in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vijaykodam/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt; or check out my blog at &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/posts&#34;&gt;https://vijay.eu/posts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me know your thoughts on this exciting new feature! 👇&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to secure microservices architecture in AWS?</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/aws-secure-microservices/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2024 00:06:59 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/aws-secure-microservices/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/ms-secure.png&#34; alt=&#34;aws-security&#34;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Image Credits:&lt;/strong&gt; Microservices architecture image made by me using draw.io&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Security in Public Cloud is utmost important. Losing access to your website or attackers deleting your database are catastrophic-company-ending-events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;shared-responsibility-model&#34;&gt;Shared Responsibility Model&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Security and Compliance is a shared responsibility between AWS and the customer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the definition from AWS documentation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AWS is responsible for the &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Security of the Cloud&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;. AWS is responsible for protecting the infrastructure that runs all of the services offered in the AWS Cloud. This infrastructure is composed of the hardware, software, networking, and facilities that run AWS Cloud services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Customer is responsible for the &lt;strong&gt;“Security in the Cloud”&lt;/strong&gt;. Customer responsibility will be determined by the AWS Cloud services that a customer selects. This determines the amount of configuration work the customer must perform as part of their security responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Refer AWS Documentation for more information on Shared Responsibility Model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;best-practices&#34;&gt;Best Practices&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily, AWS provides you with a host of security services to improve your security posture from Day One. Note that this is not an exhaustive list and &amp;ldquo;it depends&amp;rdquo; on where you run and what services you use. Here are some of the steps to secure your microservices architecture in AWS:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use AWS Shield for DDoS protection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use AWS GuardDuty for intelligent threat detection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use AWS IAM for managing identities and access to AWS resources&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use AWS WAF to protect your web applications from common exploits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use AWS Certificates Manager for encrypting website data in transit using TLS/SSL certificates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use AWS KMS keys to encrypt all EBS volumes and Aurora DB (data at rest)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use AWS Secrets Manager to store your application secrets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run all your workloads in private subnets. Allow only needed traffic using Security Groups and NACLs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If your applications need Internet connectivity to download updates then configure NAT GW in public subnet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You could also use VPC peering to isolate specific workloads in a different VPC in a different AWS account.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use Amazon Inspector to scan EC2 for security vulnerabilities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use Amazon Security Hub to automate AWS security checks and centralize security alerts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use AWS Cognito for authentication and authorization of the API requests.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use CloudTrail for audit logging.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Security should not be an after thought when building and running applications in AWS. Utilize some or all of these AWS security services to make your microservices architecture secure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What have I missed? This post assumed microservices are running in EC2 VMs. If microservices are running in Amazon EKS then it calls for a totally new approach and very long post. I will post about EKS security soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow me on LinkedIn at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vijaykodam/&#34;&gt;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vijaykodam/&lt;/a&gt; where I post articles about AWS, Kubernetes and cloud computing in general. I also post all my articles to my blog at &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/posts&#34;&gt;https://vijay.eu/posts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unlock Up to 40% AWS Cost Savings with Graviton!</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/save-costs-with-graviton/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Oct 2024 00:14:32 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/save-costs-with-graviton/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/graviton.png&#34; alt=&#34;Graviton&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Image Credits: From AWS Blog&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are multiple ways to cost optimize your applications running in AWS. One effective way to achieve this is by using &lt;strong&gt;Graviton-based instance types&lt;/strong&gt;. Graviton processor-based instances are gaining popularity as more applications and AWS services now support them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amazon EC2 instances powered by AWS Graviton2 processors provide up to &lt;strong&gt;40% better price performance&lt;/strong&gt; compared to fifth-generation x86-based instances for a wide variety of workloads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;climate-friendly-computing-with-graviton&#34;&gt;Climate-Friendly Computing with Graviton&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using Graviton also has climate benefits: it reduces your carbon footprint by using up to &lt;strong&gt;60% less energy&lt;/strong&gt; than comparable EC2 instances for the same performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By choosing Graviton-based instances over traditional x86 instances, you can unlock significant savings. Since Apple adopted ARM processors for their MacBooks, ARM has gained widespread support across operating systems and applications, ensuring seamless compatibility. AWS’s push for Graviton has further motivated the software industry to embrace ARM-based processors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AWS has been steadily expanding Graviton support across its services, making it easier than ever to leverage cost savings with ARM-based processors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;graviton-support-across-aws-managed-services&#34;&gt;Graviton Support Across AWS Managed Services&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some of the popular AWS managed services that support Graviton:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amazon EKS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amazon ECS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amazon Aurora&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amazon RDS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AWS Lambda&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amazon OpenSearch Service&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For AWS managed services where Graviton-based instances are supported, like EKS, you can create Graviton-based instances for the worker nodes. Refer to this &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/aws/aws-graviton-getting-started/blob/main/managed_services.md&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; for a full list of supported AWS services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;graviton-support-in-kubernetes-and-the-container-ecosystem&#34;&gt;Graviton Support in Kubernetes and the Container Ecosystem&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kubernetes and containers have become the de facto platform for running microservices today. Graviton is supported by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amazon EKS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Containerd&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Docker&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Helm&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grafana&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prometheus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Loki&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Istio&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ArgoCD&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Terraform&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…and many other tools. Here is the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/aws/aws-graviton-getting-started/blob/main/containers.md#ecosystem-support&#34;&gt;full list of popular software&lt;/a&gt; within the container ecosystem that explicitly supports arm64/Graviton.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, &lt;strong&gt;.NET 9&lt;/strong&gt; and many older versions support Graviton.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;operating-systems-supporting-graviton&#34;&gt;Operating Systems Supporting Graviton&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several major operating systems also support Graviton, including &lt;strong&gt;Amazon Linux 2023&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Ubuntu&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;RHEL&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;SUSE&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Alpine Linux&lt;/strong&gt;, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;try-amazon-ec2-t4g-instances-for-free-today&#34;&gt;Try Amazon EC2 T4g Instances for Free Today&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amazon EC2 T4g instances are the next generation of general-purpose burstable instances powered by Arm-based AWS Graviton2 processors. Try Amazon EC2 &lt;code&gt;t4g.small&lt;/code&gt; instances powered by AWS Graviton2 processors free for up to &lt;strong&gt;750 hours per month until Dec 31st, 2024&lt;/strong&gt;. Refer to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://aws.amazon.com/ec2/faqs/&#34;&gt;Amazon EC2 FAQ&lt;/a&gt; for additional details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this &lt;a href=&#34;https://aws.amazon.com/ec2/graviton/getting-started/&#34;&gt;step-by-step guide from AWS&lt;/a&gt;, you can adopt Graviton-based instances for your workloads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider including Graviton-based instances in your workload, whether in your Kubernetes clusters, EC2 instances, Lambda functions, or databases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Save money and save the planet.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graviton is one of several ways to optimize costs in AWS. I will cover more cost optimization strategies in future posts, so follow me to learn more about AWS, cost optimization, and Kubernetes. I also post all my articles on &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/posts&#34;&gt;my blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fastest and Cheapest Ways to Delete Millions of Files from Amazon S3</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/s3-delete-millions-of-files/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 00:42:32 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/s3-delete-millions-of-files/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Managing data in &lt;strong&gt;Amazon S3&lt;/strong&gt; can be a daunting task, especially when you&amp;rsquo;re faced with the need to delete millions of objects. Whether you’re dealing with old backups, temporary files, or simply restructuring your data, choosing the right method to delete these files is crucial. The right approach can save you time and money, ensuring that you maintain an efficient cloud environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, we’ll explore various methods to delete files from an S3 bucket, highlighting the &lt;strong&gt;fastest&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;cheapest&lt;/strong&gt; options available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;different-ways-to-delete-files-from-s3&#34;&gt;Different Ways to Delete Files from S3&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-aws-management-console&#34;&gt;1. AWS Management Console&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;AWS Management Console&lt;/strong&gt; allows you to manually delete files through a user-friendly interface. While this method is straightforward and suitable for small batches, it becomes impractical for large datasets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-aws-cli&#34;&gt;2. AWS CLI&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;AWS Command Line Interface (CLI)&lt;/strong&gt; is a popular choice for users who prefer script-based operations. You can use the following command to delete files recursively:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;aws s3 rm s3://bucket-name --recursive
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, it’s important to note that the AWS CLI is primarily &lt;strong&gt;single-threaded&lt;/strong&gt;, which can lead to slower performance when deleting large numbers of objects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-s3cmd&#34;&gt;3. s3cmd&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;s3cmd&lt;/strong&gt; is another command-line tool that offers more features than the AWS CLI. It allows for some level of parallelism, making it &lt;strong&gt;slightly faster&lt;/strong&gt; than the AWS CLI. The command for recursive deletion is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;s3cmd del s3://bucket-name --recursive
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;While it provides a better performance boost, it still doesn’t match the speed of more advanced tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;4-s3-batch-operations&#34;&gt;4. S3 Batch Operations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;S3 Batch Operations&lt;/strong&gt; are designed for large-scale tasks and can delete billions of objects. However, this method incurs additional costs based on the number of objects processed, which may not be ideal for budget-conscious users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;5-s3-lifecycle-policies&#34;&gt;5. S3 Lifecycle Policies&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;S3 Lifecycle Policies&lt;/strong&gt; are an excellent way to automate the deletion of files without incurring extra costs. You can set rules to automatically delete objects after a specified duration or based on specific conditions. However, deletions may take &lt;strong&gt;up to 24 hours&lt;/strong&gt; to execute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;6-s5cmd&#34;&gt;6. s5cmd&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;s5cmd&lt;/strong&gt; is a newer, highly parallelized tool that excels in speed. It can delete thousands of files per second and is particularly useful for massive deletions. To delete files using s5cmd, you can use the following command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;s5cmd rm s3://bucket-name/*
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;comparing-methods-fastest-vs-cheapest&#34;&gt;Comparing Methods: Fastest vs. Cheapest&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;fastest-method-s5cmd&#34;&gt;Fastest Method: s5cmd&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to speed, &lt;strong&gt;s5cmd&lt;/strong&gt; is the clear winner. It is designed for high-performance operations and leverages &lt;strong&gt;multi-threading&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;batch processing&lt;/strong&gt; to maximize efficiency. With &lt;strong&gt;s5cmd&lt;/strong&gt;, you can expect deletion rates to be up to &lt;strong&gt;100x faster&lt;/strong&gt; than the AWS CLI, making it an excellent choice for scenarios where time is critical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;cheapest-method-s3-lifecycle-policies&#34;&gt;Cheapest Method: S3 Lifecycle Policies&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If minimizing costs is your primary concern, &lt;strong&gt;S3 Lifecycle Policies&lt;/strong&gt; are the way to go. This method allows you to automate deletions without incurring additional charges. You can set lifecycle rules that trigger deletions based on file age or other criteria, making it ideal for long-term data management. While it may take longer to process (up to 24 hours), it eliminates the need for any new costs, making it perfect for &lt;strong&gt;cost-conscious&lt;/strong&gt; environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-these-methods-are-the-best&#34;&gt;Why These Methods Are the Best&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;speed-considerations&#34;&gt;Speed Considerations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For Speed&lt;/strong&gt;: When you need to delete millions of objects quickly, &lt;strong&gt;s5cmd&lt;/strong&gt; stands out due to its ability to handle multiple requests simultaneously. This is particularly advantageous in environments where data is frequently updated or removed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;cost-considerations&#34;&gt;Cost Considerations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For Cost&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;strong&gt;S3 Lifecycle Policies&lt;/strong&gt; allow you to automate data management tasks without incurring any additional charges. This is crucial for businesses looking to optimize their cloud costs while maintaining a clean and organized data structure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choosing the right method to delete millions of files from an S3 bucket depends on your specific use case. If speed is your priority, &lt;strong&gt;s5cmd&lt;/strong&gt; is the best tool for the job. Conversely, if you’re focused on minimizing costs, &lt;strong&gt;S3 Lifecycle Policies&lt;/strong&gt; offer an automated, no-cost solution for managing your data over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By understanding these options, you can make informed decisions that streamline your data management processes in AWS S3, saving both time and money in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow me on LinkedIn at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vijaykodam/&#34;&gt;https://www.linkedin.com/in/vijaykodam/&lt;/a&gt;  where I post articles about AWS, Kubernetes and cloud computing in general.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Save Hours During Amazon EKS Upgrades with This One Simple Step!</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/eks-upgrade-insights/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 01:00:19 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/eks-upgrade-insights/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/K8s.png&#34; alt=&#34;Kubernetes&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🚀 Save Hours During Amazon EKS Upgrades with This One Simple Step! 🚀&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve ever managed EKS clusters in production, you know how crucial it is to keep them updated to leverage the latest features and maintain security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🔄 But before starting an upgrade, have you checked the &amp;ldquo;Upgrade Insights&amp;rdquo; tab on the EKS cluster page?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previously, our team had to manually check for deprecations and potential issues before every upgrade, spending hours in the process. Now, with the &amp;ldquo;Upgrade Insights&amp;rdquo; feature, EKS continuously monitors audit logs, detects deprecation errors, and updates the insights daily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This small step has transformed our process and saved us countless hours of debugging and maintenance. 💡&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;✅ &lt;strong&gt;Pro tip&lt;/strong&gt;: Always review the &amp;ldquo;Upgrade Insights&amp;rdquo; tab before upgrading your clusters to ensure a smooth transition to newer Kubernetes versions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;comments&#34;&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Send your feedback by commenting on my LinkedIn post below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/posts/activity-7247354293660356609-IT7t&#34;&gt;https://www.linkedin.com/posts/activity-7247354293660356609-IT7t&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Your Public IP Address</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/projects/my-ip/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Aug 2024 12:05:32 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/projects/my-ip/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: left; margin-top: 20vh;&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div id=&#34;ip-address&#34; style=&#34;font-size: 2em; color: #007bff; margin-top: 20px;&#34;&gt;
        Fetching IP address...
    &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;script type=&#34;application/javascript&#34;&gt;
        function getIP(json) {
            document.getElementById(&#39;ip-address&#39;).textContent = json.ip;
        }
    &lt;/script&gt;

    &lt;script type=&#34;application/javascript&#34; src=&#34;https://api.ipify.org?format=jsonp&amp;callback=getIP&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fitness Calculator</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/projects/fitness-calculator/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2024 18:55:00 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/projects/fitness-calculator/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;container&#34;&gt;
    
    &lt;div id=&#34;intro-text&#34;&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            The 2 Km Walk Test is a reliable way to estimate your maximal aerobic power (VO2max) and assess your fitness level.
        &lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
            To ensure accurate results, please follow these steps before filling in the details below:
        &lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;ol&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preparation:&lt;/strong&gt; Ensure you are in good health and fit to undertake the test. Wear comfortable clothing and shoes suitable for walking.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Walk 2 Kilometers:&lt;/strong&gt; Find a flat, measured course (e.g., a track or a known distance on a path). Walk a total distance of 2 kilometers at a brisk, steady pace.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collect Your Data:&lt;/strong&gt; As soon as you finish the 2 km walk, immediately measure your heart rate (beats per minute) and note the total time taken to complete the walk (in minutes and seconds).&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enter Your Details:&lt;/strong&gt; Once you have completed the walk and collected the necessary data, fill in the information below to calculate your fitness index.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ol&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

    
    &lt;form id=&#34;fitness-form&#34;&gt;
        
        &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;label for=&#34;age&#34;&gt;Age (years):&lt;/label&gt;
            &lt;input type=&#34;number&#34; id=&#34;age&#34; name=&#34;age&#34; required&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;label for=&#34;gender&#34;&gt;Gender:&lt;/label&gt;
            &lt;select id=&#34;gender&#34; name=&#34;gender&#34; required&gt;
                &lt;option value=&#34;male&#34;&gt;Male&lt;/option&gt;
                &lt;option value=&#34;female&#34;&gt;Female&lt;/option&gt;
            &lt;/select&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;label for=&#34;weight&#34;&gt;Weight (kg):&lt;/label&gt;
            &lt;input type=&#34;number&#34; id=&#34;weight&#34; name=&#34;weight&#34; step=&#34;0.1&#34; required&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;label for=&#34;height&#34;&gt;Height (cm):&lt;/label&gt;
            &lt;input type=&#34;number&#34; id=&#34;height&#34; name=&#34;height&#34; required&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;label for=&#34;time-minutes&#34;&gt;Time to complete 2 km (minutes):&lt;/label&gt;
            &lt;input type=&#34;number&#34; id=&#34;time-minutes&#34; name=&#34;time-minutes&#34; required&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;label for=&#34;time-seconds&#34;&gt;Time to complete 2 km (seconds):&lt;/label&gt;
            &lt;input type=&#34;number&#34; id=&#34;time-seconds&#34; name=&#34;time-seconds&#34; required&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
            &lt;label for=&#34;heart-rate&#34;&gt;Heart rate at the end of the walk (bpm):&lt;/label&gt;
            &lt;input type=&#34;number&#34; id=&#34;heart-rate&#34; name=&#34;heart-rate&#34; required&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;button type=&#34;submit&#34;&gt;Calculate Fitness&lt;/button&gt;

        
        &lt;p class=&#34;disclaimer&#34;&gt;
            &lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer:&lt;/strong&gt; This tool is for informational purposes only and is not a substitute for professional medical advice, diagnosis, or treatment. Always consult your doctor or a qualified health professional before making any changes to your exercise routine or lifestyle.
        &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/form&gt;

    
    &lt;div id=&#34;results&#34; style=&#34;display:none;&#34;&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;Your Fitness Results&lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maximal Aerobic Power (VO2max):&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;vo2max-result&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; ml·min⁻¹·kg⁻¹&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BMI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;bmi-result&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fitness Index:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;fitness-index-result&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fitness Class:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;fitness-class-result&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

        &lt;div id=&#34;calculation-details&#34; style=&#34;margin-top: 40px;&#34;&gt;
            
        &lt;/div&gt;

        &lt;button id=&#34;new-calculation&#34;&gt;New Calculation&lt;/button&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flag Game</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/projects/flag-game/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2024 07:00:32 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/projects/flag-game/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;container&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;status&#34;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&#34;counter&#34;&gt;&lt;strong id=&#34;quiz-mini-counter&#34;&gt;1&lt;/strong&gt; / 10&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&#34;correct&#34;&gt;&lt;strong id=&#34;quiz-mini-correct&#34;&gt;0&lt;/strong&gt; correctly&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&#34;wrong&#34;&gt;&lt;strong id=&#34;quiz-mini-wrong&#34;&gt;0&lt;/strong&gt; wrong&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id=&#34;quiz-mini-image&#34; class=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id=&#34;quiz-mini-options&#34; class=&#34;options&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div id=&#34;quiz-mini-result&#34; class=&#34;result&#34; style=&#34;display: none;&#34;&gt;
        &lt;small&gt;
            &lt;strong&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;quiz-mini-result-correct&#34;&gt;Well done!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
            &lt;span id=&#34;quiz-mini-result-wrong&#34;&gt;False, it is &lt;strong id=&#34;quiz-mini-result-wrong-name&#34;&gt;*&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/small&gt;
        &lt;button id=&#34;quiz-mini-refresh&#34; style=&#34;display: none;&#34;&gt;Restart Game&lt;/button&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Paris 2024 Olympics Medal Tally</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/projects/medal-tally/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 16:49:32 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/projects/medal-tally/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Final medal tally for Finland and India from the Paris 2024 Olympics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;medal-tally-container&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;medal-box&#34;&gt;
        &lt;h2&gt;Finland&lt;/h2&gt;
        &lt;table&gt;
            &lt;thead&gt;
                &lt;tr&gt;
                    &lt;th&gt;Rank&lt;/th&gt;
                    &lt;th&gt;Gold&lt;/th&gt;
                    &lt;th&gt;Silver&lt;/th&gt;
                    &lt;th&gt;Bronze&lt;/th&gt;
                    &lt;th&gt;Total&lt;/th&gt;
                &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;/thead&gt;
            &lt;tbody&gt;
                &lt;tr&gt;
                    &lt;td&gt;92&lt;/td&gt;
                    &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
                    &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
                    &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
                    &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;/tbody&gt;
        &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    
    &lt;div class=&#34;medal-box&#34;&gt;
        &lt;h2&gt;India&lt;/h2&gt;
        &lt;table&gt;
            &lt;thead&gt;
                &lt;tr&gt;
                    &lt;th&gt;Rank&lt;/th&gt;
                    &lt;th&gt;Gold&lt;/th&gt;
                    &lt;th&gt;Silver&lt;/th&gt;
                    &lt;th&gt;Bronze&lt;/th&gt;
                    &lt;th&gt;Total&lt;/th&gt;
                &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;/thead&gt;
            &lt;tbody&gt;
                &lt;tr&gt;
                    &lt;td&gt;71&lt;/td&gt;
                    &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
                    &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
                    &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
                    &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;/tbody&gt;
        &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
    .medal-tally-container {
        display: flex;
        flex-wrap: wrap;
        justify-content: center;
        gap: 20px;
        margin: 20px 0;
    }
    
    .medal-box {
        background-color: #fff;
        border: 1px solid #ddd;
        border-radius: 8px;
        box-shadow: 0 2px 4px rgba(0, 0, 0, 0.1);
        padding: 20px;
        flex: 1 1 300px;
        max-width: 300px;
        text-align: center;
    }
    
    .medal-box h2 {
        margin-top: 0;
        margin-bottom: 15px;
    }
    
    .medal-box table {
        width: 100%;
        border-collapse: collapse;
    }
    
    .medal-box th, .medal-box td {
        border: 1px solid #ddd;
        padding: 8px;
        text-align: center;
    }
    
    .medal-box th {
        background-color: #f2f2f2;
    }
&lt;/style&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kubernetes 10th Birthday</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/kubernetes-10th-birthday/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jun 2024 06:06:36 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/kubernetes-10th-birthday/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/k8s10.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Kubernetes&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Celebrating 10 Years of Kubernetes!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m thrilled to be part of the incredible Kubernetes journey that started 10 years ago!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in the early days, I was deep in the world of containers. Then came the chance to build Nokia&amp;rsquo;s Digital Automation Cloud and we chose Kubernetes as the foundation. Those were wild times – Kubernetes didn&amp;rsquo;t even had ingress yet, so we had to get creative to manage incoming traffic!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest challenges we faced was managing the explosion of containers. Every company was moving workloads from VMs to containers, but there was no good way to orchestrate them. Several solutions emerged, like Docker Swarm, Mesos, and Red Hat&amp;rsquo;s Openshift (pre-Kubernetes).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, Kubernetes, with its Apache v2 license and Google&amp;rsquo;s Borg experience backing it, gained the most traction. It offered a powerful, open-source platform that could handle complex container deployments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gradually, Kubernetes became the gold standard for container orchestration. Openshift, a visionary platform, even adopted Kubernetes as its engine early on, adding features like &amp;ldquo;routes&amp;rdquo; and multi-tenancy that Kubernetes later incorporated as Ingress and RBAC. This collaborative spirit, with everyone contributing back to the core project, is what truly fueled Kubernetes&amp;rsquo; success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, cloud providers like AWS (EKS) and Microsoft (AKS) offer managed Kubernetes services, making it easier than ever to deploy and manage containerized applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The impact of Kubernetes is undeniable. Now, when companies build software, Kubernetes is the de-facto standard platform, regardless of cloud provider. It&amp;rsquo;s become the expected foundation for modern application development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s to many more years of innovation with Kubernetes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;#kubernetes #containerorchestration #cloudnative #devops #opensource&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Where Should I Deploy My K8s Cluster?</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/deploy-k8s/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 May 2020 01:00:19 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/deploy-k8s/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/K8s.png&#34; alt=&#34;Kubernetes&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week there was an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.redhat.com/en/blog/red-hat-and-aws-extend-collaboration-introducing-amazon-red-hat-openshift&#34;&gt;announcement&lt;/a&gt; about Amazon Red Hat Openshift. It is an enterprise Kubernetes (K8s) service on AWS jointly managed and supported by AWS and Red Hat. Upon reading more about the service, found out that Red Hat already has two more OpenShift services available on AWS. If you count AWS&amp;rsquo; own managed K8s service Amazon Elastic Kubernetes Service (EKS) then there are four different ways you can run a K8s cluster on top of AWS. I am sure there are many other companies providing similar managed K8s services on top of AWS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a beginner starting to use K8s this is overwhelming. This brings us to the question: &lt;strong&gt;Where should I deploy my K8s cluster?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always, the answer is: &lt;strong&gt;It Depends&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It depends&lt;/strong&gt; on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your team&amp;rsquo;s K8s expertise&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your company&amp;rsquo;s budget&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your data locality requirements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your preferred Cloud Vendor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your company&amp;rsquo;s already existing deals with Software vendors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and many more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could run your K8s cluster in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On Premises&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hybrid Cloud&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IaaS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PaaS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Others&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;on-premises&#34;&gt;On Premises&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you already own datacenters or if you have strict privacy/security requirements for making sure the data does not leave your premises then &lt;em&gt;On Premises&lt;/em&gt; solution is the way to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Install host operating system on the bare metal servers and then install K8s on top of it. Kubeadm is one option. However, be aware that this is a bare bones solution. You have to build/integrate authentication, authorization, dashboard, security, networking plugins, service mesh, storage, the list goes on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could choose to install Openshift or Rancher. These come fully loaded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Premises solutions are usually the slowest ones  to complete the installation as you have to deal  with hardware. It takes time to order, ship, install and configure them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;hybrid-cloud&#34;&gt;Hybrid Cloud&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amazon Outposts, Google Anthos and Azure Stack provide rack full of servers which you can install in your datacenter. These racks are connected to their Public cloud and you manage it just like VMs on public cloud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This option gives you the flexibility of cloud deployment with the advantage of not managing the hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep in mind that this is the most costliest option. Bill can run into millions easily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have Outposts, Anthos or Azure Stack rack on premises, you can use their managed K8s solution on top of it. Google Anthos GKE is one such option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The timeline depends on the cloud provider and honestly I have no idea about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;iaas&#34;&gt;IaaS&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you need full control of the K8s cluster and you are a pro in managing K8s then this is the option to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You install K8s on top of Amazon EC2 or Google Compute Engine or Azure Virtual Machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several K8s deployment tools like kops, kubespray or KRIB exist. You can also install Red Hat Openshift or Rancher on the virtual machines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use this option only when you have experience running k8s clusters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;paas&#34;&gt;PaaS&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If all you wanted is a K8s cluster and don&amp;rsquo;t know or don&amp;rsquo;t want to know K8s cluster management then this option is for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Managed K8s solutions like Google GKE, Amazon EKS, Amazon Red Hat Openshift, Azure AKS does fit the bill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You click a button and you get a cluster and the kubeconfig/credentials to the cluster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might want to customize some options, enable logging, move the API server to private endpoint etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually this is a good place to start for development clusters. Deploy the k8s cluster, tune it, test it, run your applications and then customize more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since this is a managed solution, you will not have full control of the cluster. You have to use whatever version they support, don&amp;rsquo;t get access to the API server or etcd servers barring some flags.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;others&#34;&gt;Others&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minikube, kind, k3s are for developments purposes. These software are light weight and are designed to run on your laptop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These solutions can be used for learning about k8s, for local testing of your applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;K8s distributions like Red Hat Openshift or Rancher can be installed on bare metal, IaaS, and  PaaS. Usually this option is useful if you have more than one type of infrastructure and you want to use the same K8s distribution everywhere. You could build automation on top of it and deploy it any where you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this blog post I have tried to cover different ways you can deploy your kubernetes cluster. This list is not exhaustive and I might have missed some options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kubernetes has become the industry standard for running containers and all the major public cloud providers have K8s services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Purpose of writing this blog post is to showcase the variety of K8s deployment options you have, be it on a bare metal server, or virtual machine or managed solution like this week&amp;rsquo;s announcement of Amazon Red Hat Openshift.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;comments&#34;&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Send your feedback by commenting on my tweet below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Where should I deploy my K8s cluster?&lt;br&gt;My new blog post on this topic.&lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/sflPzY3Rnt&#34;&gt;https://t.co/sflPzY3Rnt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Do read it and give me feedback.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Vijay Kodam (@vijaykodam) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/vijaykodam/status/1261783876596350976?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;May 16, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to login securely to your Amazon EC2 Instance?</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/how-to-login-securely-to-amazon-ec2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 14:42:15 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/how-to-login-securely-to-amazon-ec2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/secure-ec2.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Securing the Amazon EC2 instance is the first thing you have to think while creating it. This post specifically talks about how to secure SSH/RDP port on your EC2 Instances and how not to open port 22/3389 to the Internet (0.0.0.0/0).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several ways to secure your EC2 instances in AWS. Will discuss some of the popular ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When EC2 instance is running in Public subnet, disable password authentication and enable SSH keys based authentication. Secure your SSH port to allow traffic from specific subnet (Ex., 3.2.132.0/24) or your own IP address (Eg., 3.2.132.23/32) by setting security group rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.aws.amazon.com/vpc/latest/userguide/VPC_SecurityGroups.html&#34;&gt;*security group&lt;/a&gt;* acts as a virtual firewall for your instance to control inbound and outbound traffic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Problem with this method is that whenever your IP address or subnet changes you have to update your security group rules. Managing SSH keys is another task, which can get quite tricky when there are more than few EC2 instances. How to store the SSH keys safely? How to grant or revoke accesses to specific users?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another way is to use bastion host, run it in Public subnet and expose it to Internet using security group rules. Create your EC2 instances in a private subnet where there is no access from Internet and no one from outside can access it. Use security group rules to allow SSH traffic into your instance only from the bastion. This way your EC2 instance traffic is secured and only from bastion host you can access your EC2 instance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the same problem exists as before. How will you secure your SSH/RDP port on the bastion host. You will still have to manage the SSH keys to your bastion host and open inbound ports on the instance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;aws-systems-manager-session-manager&#34;&gt;AWS Systems Manager Session Manager&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Session Manager is part of AWS Systems Manager service. It gives you a browser-based CLI window to access your Windows and Linux EC2 instances without opening inbound SSH/RDP port. No need to create a bastion host. No need to manage SSH keys. Access can be granted or revoked using AWS IAM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AWS Systems Manager uses SSM agent running on the EC2 instance to manage the login and other tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SSM Agent is preinstalled, by default, on the following Amazon Machine Images (AMIs):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Windows Server 2008-2012 R2 AMIs published in November 2016 or later&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Windows Server 2016 and 2019&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amazon Linux&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amazon Linux 2&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu Server 16.04&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ubuntu Server 18.04&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amazon ECS-Optimized&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need to create relevant IAM permissions, install or enable SSM agent on the EC2 instances. Once you do it you can either acces your instance from AWS Console or AWS CLI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For detailed instructions, refer to &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.aws.amazon.com/systems-manager/latest/userguide/session-manager-getting-started.html&#34;&gt;the documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AWS Systems Manager Sessions Manager lets you manage your entire fleet of EC2 instances, audit the access, grant or revoke access for each instance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;notes&#34;&gt;Notes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beware of pressing CTRL-W if you are used to it on the bash shell. It will close your browser window. Change the keyboard shortcuts to update the shortcut.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;comments&#34;&gt;Comments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Send your feedback or comments on my tweet below:
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;How to login securely to Amazon EC2 without opening SSH port to 0.0.0.0/0.&lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/iAPvnoawwN&#34;&gt;https://t.co/iAPvnoawwN&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This tweet is used for allowing readers to comment on my blogpost. &lt;br&gt;Since it is hosted as static pages using Hugo thought this is a good way to include commenting on my blogpost.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Vijay Kodam (@vijaykodam) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/vijaykodam/status/1260837110812155904?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;May 14, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ambassador API GW and Keycloak integration</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/posts/ambassador-keycloak-integration/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/posts/ambassador-keycloak-integration/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/cloud.webp&#34; alt=&#34;cloud&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.getambassador.io/&#34;&gt;Ambassador API GW&lt;/a&gt; is an open source, Kubernetes-Native microservices API Gateway built on the Envoy Proxy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.keycloak.org/&#34;&gt;Keycloak&lt;/a&gt; is an open source identity and access management solution. Keycloak supports OpenID Connect, SAML, OAuth2 and LDAP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ambassador supports authenticating incoming requests. When configured, Ambassador will check with a third party authentication service prior to routing an incoming request. An AuthService manifest configures Ambassador to use an external service to check authentication and authorization for incoming requests. Each incoming request is authenticated before routing to its destination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this blog we will be using Keycloak as our IAM solution and integrating it with Ambassador API GW. After integrating Keycloak with Ambassador, incoming API requests will be redirected to Keycloak login page for authentication before allowing access to those APIs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;prerequisites&#34;&gt;Prerequisites:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ambassador API GW is deployed and listening for API requests. Follow the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.getambassador.io/user-guide/getting-started&#34;&gt;official instructions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;httpbin example application is configured for the URL: &lt;code&gt;http://&amp;lt;Ambassador URL&amp;gt;/httpbin&lt;/code&gt;
You can follow the instructions mentioned &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.getambassador.io/user-guide/getting-started/#3-creating-your-first-route&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure &lt;code&gt;http://&amp;lt;Ambassador URL&amp;gt;/httpbin&lt;/code&gt; is routed through Ambassador API GW and it should open &lt;code&gt;httpbin.org&lt;/code&gt; website.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; In some of the commands below, you need to substitute relevant IP or URL for Keycloak and Ambassador. You will find them in this notation: &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;Ambassador IP-or-URL&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;Your-Keycloak-IP-or-URL&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;.       Similarly there are other variables in &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt; &amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; which you need to substitute before running those commands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;set-up-keycloak&#34;&gt;Set up Keycloak&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use your existing keycloak setup if you already have. If not you can start one quicky using below instructions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Please note that below keycloak setup is not secure and is used only for testing the Ambassador-Keycloak integration. Do not use this in production. Use it at your own risk.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For testing purposes docker version of keycloak will be used for this demo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;docker run -e KEYCLOAK_USER=&amp;lt;add-your-keycloak-user&amp;gt; \
            -e KEYCLOAK_PASSWORD=&amp;lt;keycloak-password&amp;gt; \
                                  -p 0.0.0.0:80:8080 \
                                -itd --name keycloak \
                                      jboss/keycloak
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Above command will start keycloak on your Linux machine. It will set admin username, password and binds keycloak to port 80. This setup uses keycloak&amp;rsquo;s default H2 DB, which should not be used in production. Note your IP address.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Login to Keycloak by visiting &lt;code&gt;http://&amp;lt;your-ip&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; in your browser. Use the username and password supplied in the docker run command to login to Keycloak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use the existing &amp;ldquo;master&amp;rdquo; realm. Create a client and a user for our testing purposes.
Click on &lt;code&gt;Clients -&amp;gt; Create&lt;/code&gt;. Create button is on the right side of the page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/Capture6.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add &lt;code&gt;Client ID&lt;/code&gt; as &lt;code&gt;test&lt;/code&gt;. Select &amp;ldquo;&lt;code&gt;Client Protocol&lt;/code&gt;&amp;rdquo; as &amp;ldquo;openid-connect&amp;rdquo;. You can leave other fields empty. Click Save.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/Capture1.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After saving, a new window will open with more details. Turn On &lt;code&gt;Authorization Enabled&lt;/code&gt; option. It will automatically turn On &lt;code&gt;Service Accounts Enabled&lt;/code&gt; option. Leave it like that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fill &lt;code&gt;Valid Redirect URIs&lt;/code&gt; with &lt;code&gt;http://&amp;lt;Ambassador URL&amp;gt;/*&lt;/code&gt;. Click Save.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/Capture2.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/Capture8.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the same page, go to &lt;code&gt;Credentials&lt;/code&gt; tab as shown below. Note the secret which is needed when creating &amp;ldquo;ambassador-auth-client-secret&amp;rdquo; in the next section. Use it wherever &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;YOUR_OIDC_CLIENT_SECRET&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; is mentioned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/Capture4.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click Users section on the keycloak page, to create users. Add username, email and select email verified. Click Save.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/Capture9.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the same page, go to Credentials tab.  Set the new password, and turn Temporary to Off.&lt;br&gt;
Click Reset Password.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/Capture10.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When dialog window opens click Change Password.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/Capture11.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; Please note that this is done only for testing ambassador-keycloak integration.
Please do not do this in production or in any setup. Follow these instructions at your own risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now go back and click Users section in Keycloak. In the Users page, click &amp;ldquo;View all Users&amp;rdquo; and you should see the newly created user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/Capture12.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;setup-oidc-auth-integration-with-keycloak&#34;&gt;Setup OIDC Auth integration with Keycloak&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Antti Myyra for developing Ambassador-Auth-OIDC, which will be used to integrate Keycloak with Ambassador API GW.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Run below commands to clone ambassador-auth-oidc. Below you can choose to run it either in docker or in k8s. Don&amp;rsquo;t run both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;git clone https://github.com/ajmyyra/ambassador-auth-oidc.git
cd ambassador-auth-oidc/
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;running-ambassador-auth-in-docker&#34;&gt;Running ambassador auth In Docker&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use these instructions if your Ambassador API gateway is running as docker container and not in k8s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Above setup is running keycloak as docker container and listening on port 80. Below ambassador-auth-oidc docker container will listen on port 8080.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;docker run -p 0.0.0.0:8080:8080 \
      -e OIDC_PROVIDER=&amp;#34;http://&amp;lt;Your-Keycloak-IP-or-URL&amp;gt;/auth/realms/master&amp;#34; \
      -e SELF_URL=&amp;#34;http://&amp;lt;Ambassador IP-or-URL&amp;gt;:8080&amp;#34; \
      -e OIDC_SCOPES=&amp;#34;profile email&amp;#34; \
      -e CLIENT_ID=&amp;#34;test&amp;#34; \
      -e CLIENT_SECRET=&amp;#34;&amp;lt;YOUR_OIDC_CLIENT_SECRET&amp;gt;&amp;#34; \
      ajmyyra/ambassador-auth-oidc:1.3
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;running-ambassador-auth-in-kubernetes&#34;&gt;Running Ambassador Auth in Kubernetes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use this setup if you are already running Ambassador API GW in K8s.
Make sure Ambassador API GW is up and running before creating secrets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;kubectl create secret generic ambassador-auth-jwt-key --from-literal=jwt-key=$(openssl rand -base64 64|tr -d &amp;#39;\n &amp;#39;)
kubectl create secret generic ambassador-auth-redis-password --from-literal=redis-password=$(openssl rand -base64 20)
kubectl create secret generic ambassador-auth-oidc-provider --from-literal=oidc-provider=&amp;#34;http://&amp;lt;Your-Keycloak-IP-or-URL&amp;gt;/auth/realms/master&amp;#34;
kubectl create secret generic ambassador-auth-self-url --from-literal=self-url=&amp;#34;http://&amp;lt;Ambassador IP-or-URL&amp;gt;&amp;#34;
kubectl create secret generic ambassador-auth-client-id --from-literal=client-id=&amp;#34;test&amp;#34;
kubectl create secret generic ambassador-auth-client-secret --from-literal=client-secret=&amp;lt;YOUR_OIDC_CLIENT_SECRET&amp;gt;
kubectl get secrets # To confirm they&amp;#39;ve been created
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Run below commands in the root directory of ambassador-auth-oidc. This will start the ambassador-auth-oidc container on K8s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;cd ambassador-auth-oidc/
cp misc/auth-deployment.yaml.example auth-deployment.yaml
cp misc/auth-service.yaml.example auth-service.yaml

kubectl create -f auth-deployment.yaml
kubectl create -f auth-service.yaml
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Make sure ambassador-auth-oidc is up and running. Also check the logs to make sure everything is alright.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now go to &lt;code&gt;http://&amp;lt;Ambassador IP-or-URL&amp;gt;/httpbin&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It should automatically redirect you to Keycloak page for logging in.
Enter your &amp;ldquo;test&amp;rdquo; user credentials. After successful login it should automatically redirect you to &lt;code&gt;http://&amp;lt;Ambassador IP-or-URL&amp;gt;/httpbin&lt;/code&gt; page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have successfully integrated Keycloak with Ambassador API GW and tested API Authentication.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About Me</title>
      <link>https://vijay.eu/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vijay.eu/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/Community-Builder-1500px.png&#34; alt=&#34;AWS Community Builder&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;who-am-i&#34;&gt;Who am I&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m &lt;strong&gt;Vijay Kumar Kodam&lt;/strong&gt;, a techie building solutions and architectures using Amazon Web Services, cloud architecture, software development, and system design. I currently work as a Principal Engineer in Cloud Technology at Nokia, Finland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-tech-journey-so-far&#34;&gt;My Tech Journey so far&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My career journey has been a blend of deep telecom expertise and cutting-edge cloud computing skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I began by developing software for 2G CDMA systems, progressed to building 3G 1x-EVDO RNC solutions, and then transitioned to deploying 4G/5G Virtual Network Functions (VNFs) on Telco Cloud using platforms like AWS, containers and Kubernetes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the years, I’ve expanded my focus to &lt;strong&gt;Amazon Web Service(AWS), Systems Design, Solution Architecture and Kubernetes&lt;/strong&gt;, specializing in Amazon EKS to build scalable and resilient cloud-native solutions for telecom applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately dabbling with Generative AI concepts like RAG, Agents, MCP and Agentic coding CLIs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-am-i-doing-now&#34;&gt;What am I doing now&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, I’m leading and executing the end-to-end architecture and migration of a &lt;strong&gt;Private 5G platform&lt;/strong&gt; into AWS. This involves designing, implementing, and managing solutions using Amazon EKS, various AWS services, Cassandra, Grafana, Prometheus, and containerized applications. My role encompasses Cloud Architecture, SRE, DevOps, GitOps, and Systems Design, enabling me to deliver robust, scalable, and high-performing cloud-native solutions from start to finish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;worth-mentioning&#34;&gt;Worth mentioning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Got into &lt;strong&gt;AWS Community Builders program&lt;/strong&gt; for year 2025. Looking forward to learn and contribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my free time, I keep up with Generative AI and LLMs development by building solutions which you can find in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://vijay.eu/projects/&#34;&gt;AI Projects&lt;/a&gt; section of this blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;certs&#34;&gt;Certs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are my latest certs and skill badges with clickable links to verify them at Credly. Got into AWS Community Builders program for year 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.credly.com/badges/fe2052fb-5377-4e64-802a-ebae831ac54c/public_url&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/aicert.png&#34; alt=&#34;AI Cert&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.credly.com/badges/1f064197-4fc3-40cd-a67f-ec4f99eb48ea/public_url&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/ai-early-adopter.png&#34; alt=&#34;AI Early Adopter&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.credly.com/badges/4e67da8b-0e62-4a81-8bfd-914eaed218c9/public_url&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://vijay.eu/images/eks-skillbadge.png&#34; alt=&#34;EKS Skill Badge&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-opinions&#34;&gt;My opinions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thoughts and opinions shared here are solely my own and do not reflect the views of my employer.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
